<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The state of France, as it stood in the IXth yeer of this present monarch, Lewis XIIII. Written to a friend by J.E.</title>
            <author>Evelyn, John, 1620-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1328_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209097</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867997</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867997</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169778</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169778)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 176:E1328[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The state of France, as it stood in the IXth yeer of this present monarch, Lewis XIIII. Written to a friend by J.E.</title>
                  <author>Evelyn, John, 1620-1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46], 118 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. for M.M. G Bedell &amp; T Collins. at the middle Temple gate, Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.E. = John Evelyn.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the University of London (Goldsmiths'-Kress library of economic literature) and in the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169778:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE STATE OF FRANCE, As it ſtood in the IX<hi rend="sup">th</hi> yeer of this preſent Monarch, LEWIS XIIII.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written to a Friend</hi> By <hi>J. E.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T.M.</hi> for <hi>M.M. G Bedell</hi> &amp; <hi>T Collins.</hi> at the middle Temple gate, <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:169778:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169778:2"/>
            <head>The State of FRANCE, as it ſtood in the Ninth yeer of this preſent Monarch <hi>LEWIS the XIIII,</hi> Written to a Friend.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince I had firſt the honour to bee one of thoſe whoſe Converſation you have che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed with ſo many ſignall obligations, and, as it were, currents of civility; I can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:169778:3"/>think, that (when by ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny literal expreſſes and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal commands, you enjoin me to deliver ſomething in <hi>writing,</hi> touching the late ſubject of our diſcourſe) you have either cauſe to delight in my triviall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, or deſigne my diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit: For however your inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have at laſt prevailed, yet your Honor is no leſſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be tender how you publiſh my defects, whileſt in them onely (though the faults be mine) men will ſo perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily conclude your want of judgment, and condemn your Election. But you have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be diſcreet, and I ſhall then make a ſaving adventure
<pb facs="tcp:169778:3"/>of my Reputation with you, who have candor and charity not from the <hi>Multitude,</hi> but the ſtock of your own <hi>worth</hi> and ingenuous Education; of which this <hi>Eſſay</hi> will be rather an Hiſtory, then any thing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe capable to informe you, who know already ſo much more, and better, then I can poſſibly either write or relate.</p>
            <p>But to begin once, ſince it is my fate to obey you; I ſhall nothing alter the <hi>Scene,</hi> which was then Preſented you, when you were pleaſed (as it ſince appears) to take notice of thoſe caſuall Diſcourſes of mine, wherein I poſted over the
<pb facs="tcp:169778:4"/>beſt Remarks, and moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Obſervations which my weak Judgment had been able to recollect, during my ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Pererrations,</hi> and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Sojourn</hi> abroad, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this Kingdome of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor wil I vex your patience with any <hi>Topographicall</hi> Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, as being the daily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of your Contemplations, when at any time you pleaſe to refreſh your ſelf amongſt thoſe exquiſite <hi>Cards</hi> of the lateſt and moſt accurate <hi>Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> But repreſent, in as ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct a Method as I am able, what in order to Affairs (as in the Government of this moſt
<pb facs="tcp:169778:4"/>active and Illuſtrious Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie they now ſtand) I conceive to be chiefly proper and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for a Gentleman of our Nation (under the notion of a <hi>Traveller</hi>) to be able to render an accompt of at his Return: And therefore, before I proceed further, I will complie with your deſire, and ſpeak a word or two (by way of Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Digreſſion rather) of my <hi>ſentiment</hi> and opinion tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Forraign Travel</hi> in Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, wherein I ſhall alſo deal very impartially with all the world concerning mine own particular, as being (I hope) taking my long farewel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169778:5"/>
            <p>That which firſt rendred me of this <hi>Apodemick</hi> humour, (I ſhall not diſcourſe here of <hi>Mercuriall</hi> complexions, whom <hi>Phyſiognomiſts</hi> affirm to be <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidua vaga's,</hi> like my ſelf) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a certain vaine Emulation which I had to ſee the beſt of Education, which every body ſo decrying at Home, made me conceive, was a commodity onely to be brought from a far Countrie; and I cannot ſay, without a little ambition too of <hi>knowing,</hi> or at leaſt of having the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg to <hi>talk</hi> ſomething more then others could reaſonably pretend to, that had never bin out of ſight of their owne
<pb facs="tcp:169778:5"/>chimnies ſmoke: All which was a Ridiculous affectation, contracted firſt from the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Radomontadas</hi> of ſuch as have ſeen ſtrange places, and great want of diſcretion, and ſo fondly tranſported with the pleaſure onely, and temptation of <hi>Novelties,</hi> the very inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental cauſes of this unſetled extravagancy.</p>
            <p>True it is, <hi>Non omnis fert om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Tellus:</hi> for the great and good God hath diſcreetly, and very wiſely diſpoſed, in the furniſhing and adorning (as I may ſay) of this <hi>Terreſtrial Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet,</hi> having left no one part or corner thereof without ſome thing ſpecially different,
<pb facs="tcp:169778:6"/>and admirably remarkable, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the compoſition, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or uſe; all of them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their poſition, ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and effects, admirably commodious, and dependant; of which divine <hi>Oeconomy</hi> there may be infinitely more ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, then will be ſutable to this deſign, after I have infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that for theſe reſpects only, a <hi>Traveller</hi> has ſome excuſe, as well as encouragement to go abroad and ſee the world.</p>
            <p>Now then, for as much as the end of all our <hi>Appetites,</hi> wiſely <hi>inquired</hi> into, ought to be the principal <hi>Mira,</hi> and terme to all our actions, he that would travell rationally, and
<pb facs="tcp:169778:6"/>like a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> muſt induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly apply himſelf to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of ſuch things, as (through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all his <hi>Peregrinations</hi>) may reſult moſt to the profit, and Emolument of his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try at his Return; whether in the accompliſhing of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or affairs, there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more veritable, then that ſaying of <hi>Homer,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turpe quidem manſiſſe diu, vacuúmque redire.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> And therefore <hi>Peregrinatio ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi imperio, &amp; corporis miniſterio debet perfici:</hi> For ſo it was that <hi>Ptolomies</hi> young Noblemen, of whoſe rich fraight and return wee read of; travelled, and brought home with them
<pb facs="tcp:169778:7"/>wares of more value, then if they had tranſported Gold and Pearles. For the ſame cauſe PYTHAGORAS took leave of his Friends and native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to which hee afterwards returned with the Learning of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> as <hi>Strabo</hi> in his <hi>ſeventh Book</hi> and <hi>fourteenth Chapt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And not as <hi>Plinie</hi> affirmeth, <hi>Exiliis verius quam peregrinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus ſuſceptis:</hi> Nay, his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and thirſt after this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Commerce was ſo admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that the ſame Authour <hi>in Syren.</hi> tells us, he made no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>Circumciſing</hi> himſelf, that ſo hee might with the more freedom, and leſſe ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion
<pb facs="tcp:169778:7"/>pry into their profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Myſteries: For therefore were the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prieſts cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>incommunicable,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>imparticipable. Clem. Alex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such a deſigne led THA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LES, EUDOXUS, APOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LONIUS, nay PLATO him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and divers other renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſonages, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. To comprehend (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) the Myſteries of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> and <hi>Divinitie:</hi> As it ſeems, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> to be the moſt Ancient and Noble peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the whole World, both for the wiſdom of their <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,</hi> and exceeding Reverence which they bare to <hi>Learning:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169778:8"/>Theſe being indeed the fruits &amp; moſt noble acquiſitions, which a Gentleman (who is a quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied <hi>Traveller</hi>) ſhould ſtudy and endeavour to furniſh himſelfe with whilſt he is abroad.</p>
            <p>But theſe, ſome may object, are <hi>Heathen</hi> examples, <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> are content to be leſſe curious, and ſtay at home: Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> ſhall be mine Inſtance on this occaſion: and truely, it is worth the reading what he hath delivered in one of his <hi>Epiſt. ad Paulinum,</hi> you ſhall find it praefixed (amongſt ſeverall other) to <hi>Sixtus</hi> his Edition of the Bible, when (after thoſe words, <hi>Legimus in veteribus hiſtoriis quoſdam luſtraſſe
<pb facs="tcp:169778:8"/>provincias, novos adiſſe Populos, maria tranſiſſe: ut eos quos ex libris noverant, coram quoque viderent, &amp;c.</hi>) making a very ample <hi>repetition</hi> of what I have before ſpoken in the perſons of other men, and eſpecially of the incomparable <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and thoſe noble youths who went out of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> only to <hi>hear</hi> the eloquence of <hi>Livie,</hi> when <hi>quos ad contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem ſui ipſa Roma non traxerat, unius hominis fama perduxit,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring us to the eight volums which <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely written on this ſubject; thus he expoſtulates, <hi>Quid lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quar de ſaeculi hominibus,</hi> &amp;c. what do I troubling you with old
<pb facs="tcp:169778:9"/>ſtories? when the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> himſelfe, that veſſell of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and Doctour of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> diſperſed the Chriſtian Religion through ſo great a part of the world; by his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt perpetuall <hi>Peregrination,</hi> after his miraculous converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the like may be affirmed of the reſt of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and even our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: but I recommend you to the Authour. On the other ſide, as we have juſtly cenſured thoſe who meerly run abroad out of that vanity of ſpirit, and ſuch trivial conſiderations as I have already reproached in my ſelf, ſo are we likewiſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band another ſort of <hi>travellers,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169778:9"/>whoſe <hi>Cynical</hi> reſervedneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to the world that they have only minded the ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and ſatisfaction of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>Guſto:</hi> communicating uſually at their return but what may juſtly merit that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priment which <hi>Socrates</hi> once gave to a young man who would render him no accompt <hi>of all</hi> his long abſence, <hi>quod ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum peregrinatus fuerit:</hi> in the mean time, as much to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred is all maner ſtrangneſs, diſdain, Affectation and loqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, by which ſo many travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers now a days (for the moſt part) diſtinguiſh themſelves from the Vulgar, to that over acted degree of mimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb facs="tcp:169778:10"/>folly, as one would eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagine they had all this while lived in Penſion rather amongſt Apes, and Parrats, than ever either ſeen, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with perſons of Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity or Honour.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>To proeeed therfore, preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Travell <hi>ut ſuſcipiatur propter unum aliquem finem,</hi> as we have already conſtituted it: we are yet to give our young ſubject leave to be ſo far <hi>practical,</hi> as that he do not ſlip any opportunity by which he may inform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as well in things even <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanically</hi> curious and uſefull, as altogether in the Myſteries of Government and <hi>Polity,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169778:10"/>which indeed are more <hi>appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely</hi> termed <hi>Philoſophicall.</hi> Thoſe who have impoſed on themſelves, and others, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny different ſpecies of <hi>travell,</hi> as it may be ſaid to contein <hi>Theoreticall</hi> parts in it, that is to ſay, the <hi>Metaphyſicall, Phyſicall,</hi> and <hi>Mathematicall,</hi> are, in my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, more exact and tedious in their <hi>Analyſing,</hi> then perhaps they needed to have been; of them therefore I ſay no more: it ſhall be ſufficient for him whom I ſend abroad, that he conform himſelf to ſuch precepts as are onely <hi>neceſſary,</hi> not cumberſome; which Rule he ſhall likewiſe do well to obſerve even in his
<pb facs="tcp:169778:11"/>very neceſſary <hi>accoutrements</hi> and <hi>port-manteau.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then, ſuppoſing him to be a <hi>Young Gentleman</hi> apt for all <hi>Impreſsions,</hi> but from his <hi>primary education</hi> inclined to the moſt worthy: having ſet his Foot upon the <hi>Continent,</hi> his firſt ſtudy ſhall be to maſter the <hi>tongue</hi> of the Country wherein hee reſolves to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; which ought to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood perfectly, written congruouſly, and ſpoken intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently: after which he may do well to accompliſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in ſuch <hi>exerciſes,</hi> as are moſt commendable at home, and beſt attayned abroad; which will be a means of rendring
<pb facs="tcp:169778:11"/>him very fit, and apt for the generall ſociety of that <hi>Nation</hi> amongſt whom hee converſes, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the better qualifie him to frequent, without bluſh, ſuch particular places, and perſons by whom he may beſt profit himſelfe in the Myſteries of their Polity, or what other perfection they are renowned for, according as his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Genius</hi> and inclinations import him. But this hee ſhall never attain unto, till he begin to be ſomwhat ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſeaſoned in a place; for it is not every man that croſſes the <hi>Seas,</hi> hath been of
<pb facs="tcp:169778:12"/>an <hi>Academy,</hi> learned a <hi>Corran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> and ſpeaks the <hi>Language,</hi> whom I eſteem a Traveller (of which piece moſt of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> are in theſe countryes at preſent) but he that (in ſtead of making the <hi>Tour,</hi> as they call it) or, as a late Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of ours <hi>facetiouſly,</hi> but ſharply reproached, (like a Gooſe ſwimms down the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) having maſtered the <hi>Tongue,</hi> frequented the <hi>Court,</hi> looked into their <hi>cuſtomes,</hi> been preſent at their <hi>pleadings,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved their <hi>Military Diſcipline,</hi> contracted acquaintance with their <hi>Learned men,</hi> ſtudied their <hi>Arts,</hi> and is famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar
<pb facs="tcp:169778:12"/>with their <hi>diſpoſitions,</hi> makes this accompt of his time. The principal advantages which a Gentleman thus made, may obſerve, and apply, are <hi>Truth, Taciturnitie, facetiouſneſſe</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out moroſity, <hi>courage, modeſty, hardineſſe, patience, frugality,</hi> and an excellent temper in the Regiment of his health and <hi>Affections,</hi> eſpecially in point of <hi>Drink</hi> and <hi>Tobacco,</hi> which is our Northerne, Nationall, and moſt ſordid of <hi>Vices.</hi> It is (I confeſſe) a thing extreamly difficult to be at all times, and in all places thus reſerved, and as it were obliged to a Temper ſo <hi>Statick</hi> and exact among all
<pb facs="tcp:169778:13"/>converſations; nor for mine own part, do I eſteem it in all caſes neceſſary, provided a man be furniſhed with ſuch a ſtock of prudence, as he know how, and when to make uſe even of his companions ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies, (as then frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly betraying more freely their inclinations, then at times of their more ſerious recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and firſt addreſſes.) Seeing I find it generally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for a <hi>Traveller</hi> to evade ſome occaſions &amp; encounters, which (if he be at all practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal) he will <hi>nolens volens,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive himſelf ingaged into at ſome one time or other. But
<pb facs="tcp:169778:13"/>to recover this deviation, and return to our purpoſe; the vertues which our Traveller is to bring home when he doth <hi>Repatriare</hi> (as <hi>Solinus</hi> terms it) are either publick, ſuch name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as concern the ſervice of his Country; or Private, and altogether perſonall, in order to his particular advantage and ſatisfaction: and, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it <hi>Sir,</hi> if he reap ſome contentment extraordinary, from what he hath obſerved abroad, The pains, ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, watchings, Perills, journeys, ill enterteinment, abſence from Friends, and innumerable like inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb facs="tcp:169778:14"/>joyned to his vaſt expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, do very dearly, and by a ſtrange kind of extortion, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe that ſmal experience and reputation which he can vaunt to have acquired from abroad.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who boaſt of <hi>Philolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall</hi> Peregrinations (falſly ſo called) which they undertake meerly for the flouriſh and Tongue of a Place, poſſeſſe onely a Paret-vertue; It is one of the <hi>Shels</hi> of Travel (though I confeſſe, the kernel is not to be procured without it: And <hi>Topical;</hi> in which I finde the <hi>Dutch</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, generally moſt accurate and induſtrious; both of them ſerve well for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment
<pb facs="tcp:169778:14"/>of Women and Children, who are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more imported with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and <hi>Romance,</hi> then that ſolid and reall Emolument, which is (through theſe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments</hi>) to be conveyed us from abroad.</p>
               <p>It is written of <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> that hee ſaw many Cities indeed, but withall his Remarks of mens Manners and Cuſtoms, was ever preferred to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Steeples, and making <hi>Tours:</hi> It is this <hi>Ethicall</hi> and <hi>Morall</hi> part of Travel, which embelliſheth a Gentleman, in the firſt place, having a due reſpect to the <hi>Religion,</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:169778:15"/>accompliſheth a Chriſtian: In ſhort, they are all ſeverally very commendable, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions;</hi> nor ſhould a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier</hi> neglect to be ſeen in all of them: But for that my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention is here to make an Introduction onely into mine own OBSERVATIONS, I ſhall forbear to enter ſo large and ample a Field, as the through handling of this Argument would inſenſibly oblige mee to do, it having likewiſe been ſo abundantly treated of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt by every Pen which hath prevaricated on this <hi>Subject;</hi> though, in my ſlender judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:169778:15"/>and under favour, I muſt confeſſe, without any real and ingenuous ſatisfation either to Truth, or Curioſity.</p>
               <p>To conclude (Sir) and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract this tedious tranſgreſſion, I conjure you to beleeve, that I offer nothing to you in this diſcourſe, out of any the leaſt ſelf opinion, cenſure of other men, vanity, or oſtentation. No, I am aſſured you will find me far enough from that <hi>IdiopathiaE,</hi> and common di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper of <hi>Travellers;</hi> all I ſhall pretend being but to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate unto you, how I have loſt part of thoſe ſeven yeares, and more; which, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:169778:16"/>(as in truth they ought to have been) wholly exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Benefit I might have reaped from your ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety at home, I am obliged in Honour, and for Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my ſelf, to render you an Accompt how they have been diſpenſed abroad. I am very conſcious to my ſelf, how much mine owne little intereſt hath ſuffered, during mine abſence, in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your ſtayed and more Thriving <hi>Geniuſes,</hi> and ſuch as might juſtly indeed derive <hi>Characters,</hi> and Prognoſticks from a raw and unſettled ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſuch as was mine: but
<pb facs="tcp:169778:16"/>conſidering that all thoſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirory <hi>Accidents</hi> of Fo tune and the world, can no way farther extend themſelves, then to a very imperfect ſatisfaction of our regular and honeſt Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, (beſides that which they ought yeeld unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,) neither he who ſtayes at <hi>home,</hi> nor he that goes <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,</hi> is (in mine opinion) to be altogether cenſured and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and truely, he that can accommodate himſelf to ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired and contemplative a life, as certainly that of a pure <hi>Country Gentlemans</hi> is, frees himſelf of an innumerable Hoſt of troubles, and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities
<pb facs="tcp:169778:17"/>which a Traveller runs through, and is in a manner compelled to entertain. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to that of the moſt incomparable</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Claudian, De Sene Veronenſi, Epig.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Foelix qui propriis aevum tranſegit in arvis:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ipſa domus puerum quem videt, ipſa ſenem:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui baculo nitens, in qua reptavit arena</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Unius numerat ſecula longa caſae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illum non vario traxit fortuna tumultu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nec bibit ignotas mobilis boſpes aquas.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non freta mercator timuit, non claſsica miles:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non rauci lites pertulit ille fori.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Indocilis rerum, vicinae neſcius urbis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Adſpectu frui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur liberiore poli.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Frugibus alternis, non Conſule, computat annum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Autumnum pomis, ver ſibi flore notat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Idem conditager Soles, idem que reducit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Metiturque ſuo ruſticus orbe diem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ingentem meminit parvo qui germine quercum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aequae unumque videt conſenuiſſe nemus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Broxima cui nigris Verona remotior Indis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Benacumque putat litora rubra lacum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169778:17"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sed tamen indomitae vires, firmiſque lacertis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aetas robuſtum tertia cernit avum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Erret, &amp; extremos alter ſcrutetur I beros,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plus habet hic vitae, plus habet ille Viae.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>The ſerious contemplation whereof, made me ſometimes (being at <hi>Naples</hi>) break forth in this youthful, but naturall <hi>Ode</hi> againſt <hi>Travell,</hi> which I wil here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce for my finall
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Scal. lib</hi> 3. Poet c. 106. <hi>dict.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: being a ſpeech which was made to the Citizens by him that was returned home after his long travell.</note> 
                  <hi>Epibate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Happie that man who lives content</l>
                  <l>With his own <hi>Home</hi> and <hi>Continent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe chiding ſtreams his banks docurb,</l>
                  <l>Eſteems the <hi>Ocean</hi> to his <hi>Orb;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Round which, when he a walk does take,</l>
                  <l>Thinks to perform as much as <hi>Drake.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For other <hi>Tongues,</hi> he takes no thought,</l>
                  <l>Then what his <hi>Nurſe</hi> or <hi>Mother</hi> taught.</l>
                  <l>He's not diſturbd with the rude cryes</l>
                  <l>Of the
<note n="*" place="margin">The guide or Meſſenger in Italy, which in the Morning calls to Horſe.</note> 
                     <hi>Procaccia's</hi> [Up and Riſe.]</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169778:18"/>
                  <l>But charmd in down, ſleeps by the ſide</l>
                  <l>Of his chaſt Love, or Loyall Bride,</l>
                  <l>In whoſe ſmooth Arms no ſooner hurld,</l>
                  <l>But he enjoys another <hi>world;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where his Enfranchiſ'd hand may ſtray,</l>
                  <l>O're the warm ſnow, or milkie way,</l>
                  <l>And thence as oft as it declines</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="†" place="margin">Haec Comicè dicta, cave ne malè capiat.</note> Tow'rds thoſe more rich and hidden Mines,</l>
                  <l>Scornes us that travell <hi>Lands</hi> and <hi>Seas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beleeves no <hi>Kingdomes</hi> like to <hi>theſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If then at home ſuch joyes be had,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh how unwiſe are we, how mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>This I did once write, and this I ſo beleeve, (as if God bleſſe me with a ſucceſſefull Returne into my Native Country) I ſhall endeavour <hi>Vivere, non dicere huic veritati:</hi> and though the Conſcience of my perſonall inabilities, can never tempt me with the vanity to think of any publick Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement,
<pb facs="tcp:169778:18"/>for having ſpent the prime of my years and youth abroad; yet the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſatisfaction which I purpoſe and fancie to my ſelf, if I may obtaine leave but to enjoy that private condition and Fortune, which Heaven hath decided me at home, ſo that I can but rubb out of this, into a better world, without the leaſt impeachment to my <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Loyalty, Sublimi fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam ſydera vertice:</hi> I ſhall have arrived at the <hi>ſumm</hi> and very top of mine innocent wiſhes. But, if in the mean time, it be otherwiſe ordained, I have learned likewiſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb facs="tcp:169778:19"/>my ſelf unto the will of God, as being very apt to beleeve that excellent <hi>Apoph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegme</hi> of the Wiſe man, <hi>Quod Omne ſolum ſit Forti Patria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>But now to our</hi> TRAVELLER again.</p>
               <p>The principall places of <hi>EUROPE,</hi> wherein a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman may, <hi>uno intuitu,</hi> behold as in a <hi>Theater</hi> the chief and moſt ſignall Actions which (out of his owne Countrey) concerne this later Age and part of the World, are the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> comprehending <hi>Flanders,</hi> and the divided <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces;</hi> which is a perfect <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cycle</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:169778:19"/>and Synopſis of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver one may elſewhere ſee in all the other Countryes of <hi>Europe;</hi> And for this end, I willingly recommend them to be firſt viſited, no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then do thoſe who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us in the ſtudy of Hiſtory to the reading firſt of ſome au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick <hi>Epitome,</hi> or univerſall <hi>Chronology,</hi> beſore we adventure to launch forth into that vaſt and profound <hi>Ocean</hi> of volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Authours. From thence I would adviſe him to traverſe <hi>Germany,</hi> (altogether contrary to the Vulgar Method) by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that ſo uſefull Tongue, which he will find very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult,
<pb facs="tcp:169778:20"/>and with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, and many conflicts at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto, after the facill, and more ſmooth Languages are once throughly imbibed, not omitting (comparatively) even the <hi>French</hi> it ſelf. From this <hi>Region</hi> you naturally ſlide into <hi>Italy,</hi> and then Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barquing for <hi>Spain,</hi> return by a direct courſe unto <hi>Paris;</hi> where indeed, I would have the Principall aboad of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to be, not only in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the <hi>Court,</hi> and <hi>exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> acquired in that City; but alſo in reſpect to his expenſes. This may ſeem a <hi>Paradox</hi> to ſome; but for my part, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb facs="tcp:169778:20"/>found any <hi>wood</hi> to a great town; and when my Traveller hath caſt it up, and made a true Audite of all <hi>Extraordinaries,</hi> he will find, what for <hi>removalls,</hi> and what for the perill of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched and frequent <hi>colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionings</hi> (for in all other little towns his acquaintance will be univerſall, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually interviſiting, with a groſſe ingredient of <hi>Dutch,</hi>) a very little, or inconſiderable diſproportion in the total Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.</p>
               <p>Thus I propoſe <hi>France</hi> in the laſt place, for many other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects which here I purpoſely omit to enumerate, that I may
<pb facs="tcp:169778:21"/>avoid the <hi>taedium</hi> of ſo long a diſcourſe; but eſpecially, for this, that our <hi>Traveller</hi> may have the more time and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to conquer the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> and go through thoſe hardy and moſt eminent <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes</hi> which are there to bee learned in their choiceſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and native luſtre; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, with a competent tincture of their beſt conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation (for the over reſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Italian,</hi> and ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Spanyard,</hi> as well as the blunt garb of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> would in an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> be a little Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liated; for fear it become affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) he may return home,
<pb facs="tcp:169778:21"/>and be juſtly reputed a moſt accompliſhed Cavalier.</p>
               <p>To the other part of your Requeſt, Sir, that I ſhould give you ſome touches of the <hi>Low Countryes,</hi> and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (beſides the wrong I ſhould do to thoſe perfect relations al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready extant) obſerving them at a time when my judgment was not altogether ſo mature, &amp; my ſelf ſo much a <hi>Dutch Traveller,</hi> (as I have before rendred you the <hi>Character</hi>) I had rather make an <hi>Apology</hi> for what I have already, and promiſe yet to ſay, then proceed to depoſe allegations under mine own hand, of the loſſe of ſo much precious time;
<pb facs="tcp:169778:22"/>and betray mine Ignorance.</p>
               <p>Touching <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>States</hi> are ſo many, and their <hi>policy</hi> ſo different, that it would coſt me more leaſure then I have now to ſpend, to reduce, and diſcipline my ſcattered papers, and ſuch indigeſted collections as require a more formal <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod,</hi> and indeed, a better pen.</p>
               <p>Nor could your <hi>Servant</hi> in truth, have been poſſibly indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to diſcover thus far his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregious imperfections; did not your Arguments carry in them ſome ſpecious reproach, as well as your Perſon ſo great an authority over me, when you pleaſe to perſwade your
<pb facs="tcp:169778:22"/>ſelf the Advantage I muſt needs (ſay you) have had by my extraordinary Relations to Perſons of affaire, as well as what I might happly in this caſe gather lawfully out of ſuch as have the lateſt written on this Subject. So that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever (and as indeed the very truth is) I was leaſt of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive how others were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, finding it ſo difficult a <hi>Province</hi> to Regulate my ſelf, yet mine endeavor to pacifie your importunity, and render you a demonſtration of mine inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ply with any future expectation of this Nature, hath in fine, extorted this from me, as an intire reſignation &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb facs="tcp:169778:23"/>of my reputation to that obedience which I profeſſedly ow you, ever more preferring the ſatisfaction of ſo noble a Friend, to the very promulgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my own ſhame and moſt viſible imbecilities.</p>
               <p>So then (to approach our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) ſeeing all thoſe <hi>Nations</hi> (before ſpoken of) and ſeveral <hi>governments</hi> ſeem at this inſtant <hi>Epoche</hi> of time, to conſpire as it were, and deferr to the preſent <hi>Grandezza</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Empire, as likewiſe conſidering in what Relation we of <hi>England</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, I have eſteemed it beſt meriting my reflections and your patience, to finiſh, and dreſſe this <hi>Peece,</hi> as judging it
<pb facs="tcp:169778:23"/>moſt worthy the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>ERRATA's committed (in abſence of the Author, almoſt the whole time this Book was in Preſſe) the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Reader is deſired to reform, thus: Page 8 in marg. for <hi>ate</hi> read <hi>late.</hi> pag. 10 in mar. r. <hi>Character.</hi> p. 27 r. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſchal.</hi> p. 32 l. ult. a [,] betwixt Deüanes Tailles p. 34 lin. 9 a parenthelis at certain (&amp;c. pag. 16 r. <hi>Treaſurers</hi> p. 36 r. of <hi>the</hi> Tailles p. 50 r. which <hi>is drivin of that Trade,</hi> pag. 51. lin. 1. a parentheſis at (for &amp;c p. 52 in mar. r. Cap. p 53 r. <hi>whom we</hi> p. 56. after <hi>Legate</hi> dele [,] p 57 r. <hi>it</hi> will be &amp;c p. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> r <hi>France.</hi> p 62. r. <hi>each</hi> Souldiers head. <hi>ibid.</hi> read <hi>in Gariſon.</hi> p. 68. r. <hi>their</hi> hands. p. 69 r. <hi>but for that</hi> p 70 after <hi>State Affairs</hi> dele[:] <hi>Ibid.</hi> r. <hi>of far greater</hi> &amp;c. p 73 r. <hi>poverty.</hi> p 74. r. <hi>obiects</hi> p 78 r. <hi>are</hi> eſtimated. p. 81. dele <hi>or</hi> before <hi>intereſts</hi> p. 87 for <hi>of</hi> ſtrength r. <hi>a</hi> ſtrength. p. 90 r. <hi>muſt</hi> of conſequence &amp;c. with divers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o her miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpunctations.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169778:24"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169778:24"/>
            <head>The STATE OF FRANCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Will begin with a ſaying of <hi>Nich.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Machiavels</hi> ſaying of <hi>France,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavel: La Corona è li Regi di Francia ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no hoggi più richi, &amp; più potenti che mai.</hi> The Crown and Kings of <hi>France,</hi> are at this day more opulent and mighty then ever they were; ſo that Prince of <hi>Polititians,</hi> a great while ſince: and without contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, had he any reaſon to give it out ſo in his time, we have much more to affirm the ſame in theſe our dayes, wherein they have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merged,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169778:25"/>as it were, the ſole victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and Flouriſhing Nation of <hi>Europe,</hi> in whoſe boſome <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> hath even built this goodly Kingdome.</p>
            <p>That where a Soveraigne Prince is able to maintain an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and unarbritrary juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction over his ſubjects,
<note place="margin">Victory and greatneſſe the effect of ſoveraigne power and prudent Councell.</note> managed with an active and prudent <hi>Councell,</hi> there, and rarely elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, doth victory and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bleſſe and favour a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with any permanent ſucceſs, is a verity moſt demonſtrable: whether we reflect on the preſent Age,
<note place="margin">From the example of the Romans, Athenians.</note> or thoſe frequent Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the <hi>Romanes</hi> and <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> whoſe deſertion and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning of their Royall ſuperiours fomented ſuch confuſion and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction amongſt the <hi>Noblemen</hi> and <hi>Plebeians,</hi> as could never be afterwards compoſed even to the ultimate deſtruction and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>cataſtrophe</hi> of thoſe moſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Republicks.</p>
            <p>But in vaine do wee ſeek for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169778:25"/>other Inſtances of this great Truth, then the preſent progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and almoſt quotidian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of the now flouriſhing <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Family; which,
<note place="margin">and Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manians; though now a dangerous Truth.</note> as it is the moſt invincible upon earth, ſo muſt we needs acknowledg it to be the moſt <hi>independent</hi> and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute which theſe later times have likely produced unto us. But for that this is a Verity which may now adayes coſt a man his <hi>Teeth</hi> (to loſe nothing elſe in the purſuit) I ſhall proſecute it no further then may ſerve to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate what it is which hath of late rendred ſo potent and <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandized</hi> this preſent aſpiring, &amp; formidable Monarchy, <hi>France;</hi> of which I ſhall next eſſay to give a brief <hi>Character.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, as in deſcription of <hi>Bodies naturall, Diſſections</hi> begin ever with the ſupreme and more noble Regions; ſo in <hi>anatomiſing</hi> the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> which conſiſts of a Body <hi>Politick,</hi> I will commence with the Head, that is,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169778:26"/>the <hi>King;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Kings of France abſolute ſince Lewis the 11. his ſaying.</note> whom <hi>here</hi> I may call as <hi>Abſolute,</hi> ſince <hi>Lewis the Eleventh</hi> hath ſo long ſince (to uſe his own <hi>expreſsion</hi>) put them <hi>hors de page;</hi> that is, freed them from that grand authority, which, till his time, the <hi>Parliament</hi> indeed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed over them; ſo that now the ſame reaſon which moved the late <hi>kings</hi> to <hi>depoſe</hi> or tranſlate Saint <hi>Denys</hi> their ancient <hi>Patron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S Denys the patron of F. depoſed, to gratifie the B. Virgin.</note> and to put his Kingdome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally under the protection of the <hi>bleſſed Virgin,</hi> is eſteemed good reaſon,
<note place="margin">For with theſe words of courſe, the Secretary (it ſeems) concluded the Arreſt, whereby it was confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which gave many occaſion to reproach it.</note> and ſufficient Logick for all his preſent Commands whatſoever: <hi>Car tel eſt noſtre bon plaiſir:</hi> for ſuch is our good will and pleaſure.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sic volo, ſic jubeo, Stat pro Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Voluntas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For ſo we will, ſo we command,</l>
               <l>Our will do's for our Reaſon ſtand.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Monarchy of France (from a <hi>Democratick</hi> ſtate) was founded <hi>Anno,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of Fr. when foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> 420. and hath continued it ſelf under three ſeverall <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169778:26"/>viz. of <hi>Meroüeſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">cont nued under three Races.</note> 
               <hi>Charle mayn</hi> ſon of <hi>Pepin,</hi> and laſtly, <hi>Hue-ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet;</hi> from whom this Royal houſe of <hi>Bourbon</hi> derives its ſucceſſion, branched from <hi>Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Clermont</hi> fourth ſon of, Saint <hi>Lewis;</hi> ſo that the King at preſent Reigning is the ſixty fifth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of <hi>France,</hi> without that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Feminine Sex</hi> hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily intervened;
<note place="margin">no woman intervening.</note> as they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm at leaſt,
<note place="margin">From the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick law; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a meer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validate the title of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</note> from a very invete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Law, which they intitle the <hi>Salique,</hi> being indeed but a meer <hi>Romance</hi> of their own feigning, a piece of <hi>legier de main,</hi> by which they have ſo long pretended with the great ſhadow of Juſtice to elude and invalidate the title of our former and ancient Kings of <hi>England,</hi> as to <hi>ſucceſsion</hi> in the right of their Mothers and Wives.</p>
            <p>Touching that other Legend of their <hi>Sainte Ampoule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">as well as their Sainte Ampoule.</note> which in the time of <hi>Cloüis firſt Chriſtian King of France</hi> was (as they give out) brought by an Angel from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169778:27"/>Heaven, &amp; reſerved at <hi>Rhemes</hi> for the Royal <hi>Chriſme,</hi> we will give it leave to paſſe as a vulgar, yet not impolitick errour, or imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent tradition:
<note place="margin">The Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Fr. ſometimes married to private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Titles and Surnanes.</note> however, by the device aforeſaid, the <hi>Daughters</hi> ſucceed not to the Crowne, ſome of them having oftentimes marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves unto private men, but ſtill reſerved their Titles, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Surname of France,</hi> which it ſeems is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour permitted them during life, to ſhew from what <hi>ſtock</hi> they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally derived.
<note place="margin">And the Queens ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Regency du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority of the Kings.</note> Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this, the <hi>Queens</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> are uſually admitted to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency</hi> during the <hi>Minority</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> which is at the age of fourteen <hi>years, in choative;</hi> until which term, they with their <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi> adminiſter the publick Affairs of <hi>State,</hi> without equall or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule.</p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Title</hi> or <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct</hi> of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The title of the F. Kings</note> which is <hi>moſt Chriſtian,</hi> and <hi>eldeſt ſon of the Church,</hi> they make no
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169778:27"/>ſmal boaſts; for not having been a <hi>complement</hi> (as they name it) ſent them from <hi>Rome,</hi> as were thoſe of other <hi>Kings;</hi> but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, time out of Mind, from their own vertue, merits, and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Eldeſt ſon of France</hi> is during the life of his Father,
<note place="margin">of his eldeſt ſon.</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> from a ſtipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as it ſeems) made with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert:</hi> who bequeathed that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince conditionally to <hi>Philip de Valois.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpeak ſomething particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly of this little-great Monarch <hi>Lewis the fourteenth,</hi> born <hi>Sept.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Birth and Character of the preſent King.</note> 5. 1638 after the Queen his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had been <hi>above</hi> twenty yeers without Iſſue, as his production was almoſt miraculous (not to repeate here any bold diſquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with thoſe who give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a liberty in theſe days, to ſpeak evil of dignities) ſo is his perſon a Character doubtleſs of no leſſe Majeſty, and fair hopes; and certainly, if his Education be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169778:28"/>fitted to the prognoſticks of his Nature, he cannot but emerge a Prince of ſingular Qualities and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregious perfections: This I am willing to adde from that <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick</hi> and Artificial breeding,
<note place="margin">Artifice of the French Queen and publick mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the are kings Education.</note> which men <hi>conceive</hi> ſome of his progenitors and neereſt relation received; that ſo not being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſo dextrous and knowing in <hi>King-craft,</hi> as their high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling required, they might with leſs ſuſpicion and more eaſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be governed, by the counſels and inclinations of ſuch, whoſe <hi>myſtery</hi> and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it hath ever been to continue by this means their Greatneſſe, and reinforce their Authority.</p>
            <p>This preſent King hath one onely Brother,
<note place="margin">Duke of Anjou his Character.</note> who is called the <hi>Duke of Anjou:</hi> but more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi>Monſieur;</hi> a child of an extraordinary prompt and ready ſpirit.</p>
            <p>The other principall branches of this Royall Family,
<note place="margin">Duke of Orleans his character.</note> are in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169778:28"/>firſt place, <hi>Gaſton Jean Baptiſt,</hi> the Kings <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle,</hi> and <hi>Duke of Orleans,</hi> Lieutenant General of the K. and Governor of <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doc;</hi> the ſame, who during ſo many years as his Brother was without <hi>off-ſpring,</hi> had thoſe fair hopes of a <hi>Crown;</hi> which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his merit and abilities for ſuch a jewel be commonly diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to his no great advantage, certainly there is no man alive in competition with him for his exquiſite skill in <hi>Medailes,</hi> To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pical <hi>memory,</hi> and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry knowledge in <hi>Plants:</hi> in both which faculties the moſt reputed <hi>Antiquaries</hi> &amp; greateſt <hi>Botaniſts</hi> do (and that with reaſon) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg him both their Prince, and ſuperiour.</p>
            <p>The Eldeſt daughter of this <hi>Duke,</hi> is <hi>Anne Marie D'orleans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle her character.</note> particularly called <hi>Mademoiſelle, Sans queüe per eminentiam,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt in praeeminence, and (after the <hi>Queen</hi>) greateſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in <hi>France,</hi> to give whom the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169778:29"/>
               <hi>Epithetes</hi> of her great worth, were to ſpoile all her <hi>ſex</hi> of their Praiſes, and make her as much envied, as ſhe is indeed juſtly to be admired.</p>
            <p>The next in Blood and Ranke is <hi>Loüis de Bourbon</hi> the Prince of <hi>Condy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prince of Condy his deſcent and haracter.</note> the ſon of <hi>Henry de Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> who (to ſo little purpoſe) was yet ſo miraculouſly ſaved in the laſt bloudy and inhumane <hi>Pariſian Maſſacre.</hi> This Prince is <hi>Grand Maiſtre of France,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Bourgongne and Bery,</hi> deſcended by a direct line maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line of <hi>Francois de Bourbon,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond brother of <hi>Antonee of Bourbon,</hi> Earle of <hi>Marle,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>Duke of Vandoſme,</hi> and <hi>King of Navarr,</hi> the Father of <hi>Henry the Great,</hi> and of <hi>Charlot Catherine de la Trimoüille,</hi> his ſecond Wife.</p>
            <p>A Prince, whoſe merit in field, and ſucceſsfull Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, high extraction, and extraordinary parts, prompt him ſometimes to Enterpriſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169778:29"/>the duty or praiſe of a Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſubject; for their lives not a more Ambitious young man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, having outlived his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, once chaſed his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my the Cardinal; and not ſatisfied with this revenge (or what ever other aſſurances the <hi>State</hi> can render him) puts fair by a freſh Rebellion to ſpeede a proſperous <hi>Traytor;</hi> or perfect his Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</p>
            <p>His brother is <hi>Armand de Bourbon</hi> Prince of <hi>Conty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prince of Conty his Character.</note> ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſigned for the <hi>Church,</hi> but <hi>ſuſceptible</hi> of any other advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; a prince of a weak fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick and conſtitution, but ſound intellectuals. They have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a Siſter called, <hi>Mary,</hi> Wife to the Duke <hi>de Longuevill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How the daughters of <hi>France</hi> have been diſpoſed of into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Spain, Savoy, Mantoa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">daughters of F. how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of.</note> &amp;c. will be here ſuperfluous to relate.
<note place="margin">The naturall iſſue of the K of F. how eſteemed.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the <hi>Natural iſſue</hi> of the Kings of <hi>France</hi> (who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169778:30"/>in this kind Country in very great Reputation and place, ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their birth, (by their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide) I cannot learne that the late King had any; nay, it is reported, he did ſo abhorre <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liardize,</hi> that he ſcarce thought any other act to be ſin in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of it: contrary to the opinion of his wiſe Counſelor and <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall de Richlieu,</hi> who (as I have ſometime heard) did uſe often to ſay, that a <hi>Concubine was the honeſt mans recreation:</hi> a Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Aphoriſm,</hi> and ſpoken like a Churchman.</p>
            <p>Now to ſay ſomething of the <hi>Soveraignety</hi> of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of the French Kingdome, how it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute.</note> we will ſtep a little back, and ſee by what meanes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees it became ſo abſolute.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the <hi>Nobility</hi> of <hi>France</hi> were in a manner free and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Princes (for ſuch was heretofore the moſt part of them) how are <hi>Hiſtories</hi> loud with their carriages and deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment towards their Soveraigns?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169778:30"/>What checks upon every occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion were they ready to give them? Witneſſe thoſe frequent impreſſes of a certain Duke of <hi>Gienne, Bourbon, Bretagne,</hi> and others of the ſame rank; nor hath theſe later times exempted the Crown it felf from the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequences which ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fortified <hi>Towns, Governments,</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> of importance have ſo often menaced, and in effect nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly brilding the head of Majeſty; untill the defunct and great <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall de Richlieu</hi> found out a ſpeedy and fortunate expedient to reduce them to obedience,
<note place="margin">C. <hi>de Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu</hi> his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing it to that inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency.</note> and that not onely by ſubjugating the <hi>Poſts</hi> themſelves, which he performed by ſtrength; but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by ſo dextrouſly intereſſing the <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>refractory Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> both by honours and blood, to the Court and his faction, which he did by policy: In <hi>fine,</hi> he ſo handled the Cards, that the better ſort of people became tractable out of meer reſpect to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169778:31"/>their Relations; and the meaner by an inevitable conſtraint, as well as the example of their <hi>Chiefs,</hi> were compelled to a due ſubmiſſion; ſo that now the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty of <hi>France</hi> is become ſo <hi>Independent</hi> and abſolute, that albeit it do ſtill reteine a ſhadow of the ancient form, yet it is, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, a thing heavenly wide and different:
<note place="margin">The Kings abſolute power, both,</note> For in the Kings ſole power it is to <hi>reſolve</hi> of, and <hi>diſſolve warrs;</hi> by him are the <hi>Lawes interpreted; Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of grace,</hi> of <hi>Naturality,</hi> and other <hi>Acts</hi> given out; he it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth <hi>Taxes,</hi> from which (by a ſpeciall decree) the <hi>Church</hi> her ſelfe is not exempt;
<note place="margin">In Church and State.</note> nay, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the <hi>Pope</hi> his own holineſſe conſent not; from all whoſe Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall <hi>Cenſures, Fulmina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>Anathema's</hi> he eſteems himſelfe alſo priviledged, and therefore nominates all <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all perſons</hi> to their preferments and dignities: Notwithſtanding all this; the handſomer to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169778:31"/>and apparell theſe his <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunties,</hi> and render them at the leaſt <hi>ſpecious</hi> proceedures of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of Juſtice &amp;</note> he permits none of his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts</hi> to paſſe as <hi>authentick</hi> untill the Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> (who is abſolutely at his devotion) have firſt verified them; a favour, this likewiſe out of complement too,
<note place="margin">Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
               <hi>non tam neceſſitatis, quam huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis,</hi> as a <hi>Civilian</hi> (whoſe gloſſe it is) hath warily termed it.
<note place="margin">Parliament of <hi>France</hi> a name only.</note> So that as for the Parliaments of <hi>France</hi> (beſides the name and <hi>Formality</hi>) there is in truth, now no ſuch thing in Nature; which together with their ancient liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, how deſervedly they loſt them, may be eaſily diſcovered in their frequent <hi>Rebellions.</hi> In a word, he who would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, and without more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe underſtand by what <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> the <hi>Kings of France</hi> impoſe on their <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> may ſee it <hi>ſummarily,</hi> yet very legibly ingraven by that forementioned <hi>Cardinall,</hi> upon that excellent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169778:32"/>
               <hi>Artellery,</hi> which defend his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>Citadell</hi> at <hi>Haver de grace</hi> in <hi>Normandy;</hi> where you may run and read the beſt of <hi>Tenures,</hi> as the times are now, in this <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigraph, —RATIO <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MA REG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M,</hi> though for this ſlavery of theirs, they may in ſome degree thank our <hi>Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">By what means diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed.</note> whoſe forces being embowel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led amongſt them, hindred the Aſſembling of the <hi>Three Eſtates</hi> (as they ſhould have done:) whereupon the <hi>King</hi> being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to make his ſimple <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts</hi> paſſe for <hi>Authentick Laws</hi> (although this power were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to him during his wars on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) was the reaſon why the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple could never recover or ſeize on them ſince. A Jewel this of too great value (ſome think) to bee intruſted to one perſon, upon what pretence or neceſſity ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. To the <hi>King</hi> and his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Iſſue, in dignity and rank, are the <hi>Dukes</hi> and <hi>Peers</hi> of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:169778:32"/>
            <p>But firſt, It is to be obſerved, that the <hi>Princes of the Blood</hi> of this Kingdom poſſeſs their Lands and Revenues under the name of <hi>Appanage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Crown by Appanage.</note> and not as abſolute Proprietaries; by which means all their <hi>Eſtates</hi> return again to the <hi>Crown</hi> by the right of <hi>Reverſion,</hi> to the end that the <hi>domaine</hi> abide intire; and for other the like reaſons: the Duke of Sully <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Richmont,</hi> heretofore called <hi>Bois Belle</hi> (on which there hangs a Story) only excepted.</p>
            <p>We will paſſe over their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, which would be extreme dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to inveſtigate,
<note place="margin">Their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</note> and proceed to their Authority, which was firſt eſtabliſhed by <hi>Hughes Capet</hi> and his deſcendants, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon obliged them to hold their Lands of the <hi>Crown</hi> immediately; by which means he alſo gained many that before were diſaffected to him; as the Earls of <hi>Flanders,</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rheims,</hi> and divers others, who had been at the firſt great oppoſers of this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169778:33"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi> Now of theſe <hi>Peers,</hi> there were at the firſt Twelve onely ordained:
<note place="margin">and Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</note> to wit, <hi>ſix</hi> of the <hi>Spiritualty,</hi> and as many of the <hi>Temporalty:</hi> but at this day their number is become indefinite, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending ſolely on the pleaſure of the King: And theſe are ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not for that they pretend to any equality of Dignity with their Soveraign, but their mutual <hi>parity</hi> in authority one amongſt another.</p>
            <list>
               <head>The Eccleſiaſticks were</head>
               <item>1 <hi>Th' Archbiſhop and Duke of Rheims.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</note>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>The Biſhop and Duke de Laon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>The BP and Duke de Langres.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>The Biſhop and Earl of Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vais.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>The Biſhop and Earl of Noyon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 <hi>The Biſhop and Comte de Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons</hi> in Champagne.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſix Temporal were</head>
               <item>The <hi>Dukes</hi> of 1 <hi>Bourgongne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Temporall.</note>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Dukes</hi> of 2 <hi>Normandie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Dukes</hi> of 3 <hi>Guyenne.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:169778:33"/>
               <item>The <hi>Compts</hi> of 4 <hi>Tholouſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Temporal.</note>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Compts</hi> of 5 <hi>Champagne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Compts</hi> of 6 <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe <hi>twelve Peers</hi> compoſed likewiſe in times paſt the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of France; from whence it is to this day called (as once with us) the <hi>Court of Peers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities &amp; priviledges.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now, amongſt ſundry other <hi>Immunities</hi> &amp; <hi>Priviledges</hi> which they injoy, this is none of the leaſt, that they can neither be diſpoſed of, nor <hi>appealed</hi> in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but onely in the Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> where they have their Places as the <hi>Princes of the Blood</hi> have: for before the Inſtitution of that high <hi>Tribunal</hi> in this Kingdom, the <hi>Peers</hi> were thoſe which judged all Cauſes that were ordinarily brought before the <hi>King;</hi> nor did he manage any thing elſe either in War or Peace, without their ſpeciall aid and aſſiſtance. Moreover, this digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſome hath been granted for <hi>life,</hi> ſome <hi>perſonal,</hi> others onely
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169778:34"/>to the <hi>Males deſcending,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Women ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Paireries.</note> ſome for <hi>ever;</hi> yea, and even <hi>women</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are alike capable of <hi>Paire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It would take up too much time, ſhould I trouble you with their ſeverall Functions and <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> at the <hi>Coronation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Charges at the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> more fit for an <hi>Herauld,</hi> than an <hi>Hiſtorian;</hi> this onely is obſervable, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit there were never ſo many <hi>Peers</hi> preſent, Thoſe onely who bare the Titles of the ſix <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,</hi> and ſix <hi>Temporall</hi> before noted, <hi>officiate</hi> at the Ceremony; for which very purpoſe, thoſe who are wanting, or extinct, have yet their <hi>Repreſentatives,</hi> who upon this occaſion ſtand for, and ſupply their Perſons.</p>
            <p>We have ſpoken now of the King and prime Nobility;
<note place="margin">The Crown of France, and Officers belonging to it.</note> Let us next ſurvey the <hi>Crown,</hi> and the prime Officers thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing.</p>
            <p>The late Author of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat de France</hi> hath divided them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169778:34"/>into <hi>three Ancients, three Modern,</hi> and <hi>three Domeſtique;</hi> which truly, is not an unequall <hi>tricho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy:</hi> But for that I intend to perfect what I have already eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed touching the <hi>Court,</hi> I wil commence with the <hi>three laſt</hi> in this partition, and ſo come to thoſe which more immediately appertaine to the <hi>State</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <note place="margin">The Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note>
            <list>
               <head>The three Domeſtick Officers and Charges are,</head>
               <item>The <hi>Grand Maiſtre of France,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Grand Chambellan of Fr.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Grand Eſcuyer of France.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>office of the Grand Maiſtre de France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The office of the Grand Maiſtre de France.</note> is ſuperintendent of the Kings houſe, and hath abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute juriſdiction over all the domeſtick officers and Proviſions of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> table; and is a place of ſo ſupreme Authority, that it is ſeldome conferred ſave upon one of the Princes of the Blood; The <hi>Prince of Condy</hi> at preſent undeſervedly inheriting his fathers charge therein.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169778:35"/>
            <p>Under the <hi>Grand Maiſtre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Subordinate officers to him.</note> are many ſubordinate officers; as <hi>Maiſtres de Hoſtel, Butlers, Carvers, Gentlemen waiters,</hi> and a whole Regiment of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which are reduced to no certain number: One thing is to be noted,
<note place="margin">ceremony at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eath of the king.</note> that when the King dyes, the <hi>Grand Maſtre</hi> breaketh his ſtaffe of office, not only as an embleme of the diſmiſſion of the reſt, but likewiſe to ſhew that their charges are only depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant upon the life of the <hi>King,</hi> albeit afterward, the <hi>ſucceſſor</hi> for the moſt part re-eſtabliſh them.
<note place="margin">The high Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berlain and officers ſubordinate to him.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Next to the <hi>G. M.</hi> is the <hi>High Chamberlain</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who hath the ſuperviſall and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of all officers of the Kings <hi>Bedchamber</hi> and <hi>Wardrobe,</hi> gives or denyes acceſſe to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie; under him there are four chief Gentlemen of the Chamber, called, <hi>les quatres premiers gentils hommes de la chambre du Roy;</hi> one of theſe ever lies in the <hi>Kings
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169778:35"/>Bedchamber,</hi> or very neer to it. Under theſe are the Maſters of the Wardrobe, very lucrative places, to whom are ſubordinate the Pages, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the <hi>Grand Eſcuyer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Grand Eſcuyer, his authority.</note> or Maſter of the Horſe, ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the <hi>Premier Eſcuyer</hi> and other Officers of the ſtables; his charge it is to march on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back before the King, bearing a Sword and Belt, when his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty entreth into any City; but in thoſe towns which have a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> he carries (in place thereof) a Caſque of blew velvet <hi>ſemeèd</hi> with flowre <hi>de lys,</hi> his own horſe Capariſoned with the like. He pretends alſo authority over the Maſters of the <hi>Poſt,</hi> Offices of wonderfull gain; but it is now otherwiſe ſettled. The <hi>Maſter of the Horſe hath</hi> likewiſe under him four and twenty <hi>Pages,</hi> who being the ſons of prime Noblemen, are educated in all ſuch exerciſes as become their quality. The <hi>Grand Eſcuyer</hi> is at preſent the <hi>Prince of Harcourt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169778:36"/>
            <p>The <hi>Premier Eſcuyer</hi> (whom I have before mentioned) hath particular care of the Kings <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Stable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Premier Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuyer.</note> where the coach hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are kept, as alſo over the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, who be no leſſe then fifty in number, and the Kings <hi>foot-men;</hi> in effect he commands equally both the great and little ſtables, ſo that the charge of the <hi>Premier Eſcuyer</hi> is not much inferiour to that of <hi>Maſter</hi> of the Horſe himſelf.
<note place="margin">Secretaries of the Kings Chamber and Cabinet</note>
            </p>
            <p>The King hath likewiſe foure <hi>Secretaries</hi> of his <hi>Chamber,</hi> and three of his Cabinet: to ſpeak truth, the multitude of thoſe who ſtile themſelves <hi>Secretaries</hi> to the King, is ſuch, that what with the greatneſſe of their number, and inconſiderableneſſe of moſt of their perſons, the dignity of the charge is extremely Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>The Kings <hi>Bibliothecarius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecarius, Controlers Treaſurers, Mareſhals des Loges.</note> 
               <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendant of the Moveables of the Crown, Controlers, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers, Mareſhals des Loges, la
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169778:36"/>Capitaine de la Porte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Capitain de la porte, &amp;c.</note> who hath under him a guard of fifty Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berds, &amp;c. and of other inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our officers of all ſorts under thoſe above five hundred more, though never half of them wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at a time, and ſo not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly eating at Court,
<note place="margin">Order, ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, &amp; hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality, of the Engliſh Court pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred.</note> as did heretofore moſt of the officers of the <hi>Kings of England;</hi> the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, hoſpitality, order, and decent magnificence of whoſe ſervice and attendance in this kind, I am confident no Court of Europe hath ever approach'd or Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell'd.</p>
            <p>There are likewiſe of Church men,
<note place="margin">The Great Almoner.</note> 
               <hi>The Greate Almoner of France,</hi> upon whom depend all of that Robe in the Court; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him is alſo the <hi>Premier Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chaplains, Clerks, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors.</note> and ſubordinate to him the ſeverall <hi>Chaplains, Clerks, Confeſſors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now before I proceed, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I ſhould ſpeak of thoſe Royal officers which ſuperintend the <hi>Kings pleaſures</hi> and ordinary
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169778:37"/>Recreations,
<note place="margin">pertaining to the Kings pleaſure: as Veneur, Fau connier' &amp;c.</note> ſuch is the <hi>Grand Veneur</hi> and <hi>Fauconnier,</hi> the chief <hi>Hunter,</hi> and maſter of the <hi>Game,</hi> places not only of very great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but alſo of Command; but a word of them ſhall ſuffice, as offices rather of dignity then policy.</p>
            <p>Touching the officers belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in particular to the <hi>Queens houſhold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Officers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Queens in particular much like thoſe of the Kings.</note> I ſhall herein like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe much contract my ſelf, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo amply diſcourſed of thoſe which appertain unto the King; and the rather, in regard that in moſt of the <hi>ſubalternate,</hi> they ſo much reſemble the one the other:
<note place="margin">Except maids of honour. Knights, &amp;c</note> Yet ſhe hath different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one <hi>Dame d' Honneur,</hi> of Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinaries many more; ſix <hi>Maids of Honour,</hi> twelve <hi>Chamber</hi>-maids called <hi>Filles de la Reyne:</hi> a <hi>Knight</hi> of <hi>Honor</hi> divers <hi>Maſters, Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers,</hi> &amp; <hi>carvers;</hi> a chief <hi>Groom,</hi> under whom are a great many <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and footmen:</hi> alſo <hi>Secretaries, Treaſurers,</hi> &amp;c. She hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe her <hi>Grand Aumoſnier</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169778:37"/>a <hi>Premier Aumoſnier,</hi> Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, and the like, as before was ſaid of the King.</p>
            <p>And now having ſurveied the Principal officers of the <hi>Court,</hi> I know you are ready to enquire of me where the Guard of this great Monarch is all this while? I will but only mention the <hi>grand Prevoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Grand prevoſt, his command.</note> at preſent the <hi>Mareſhal d' Hoquencourt,</hi> whom I may not omit, and then I will draw them forth in their ſeveral or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:</p>
            <p>Not only the <hi>Grand Prevoſt</hi> is an office which extends it ſelfe over all the officers (already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) which belong to his Majeſties Houſhold, but it hath likewiſe command abſolute for ſix leagues round about <hi>Paris,</hi> and the <hi>Court,</hi> every way, which is in truth a very great and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble juriſdiction; beſides he is judg of all cauſes, as well <hi>civills,</hi> as <hi>criminels,</hi> which are incident in Court, and hath for this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect two <hi>Leutenans,</hi> Fifty <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:169778:38"/>of the Kings Guard, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall other officers: To him appertaineth the impoſing of the price of <hi>Bread, wine, fleſh, fiſh, hay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Guard of the King of F.</note> 
               <hi>oates,</hi> with ſundry other very important priviledges. But behold, here comes the <hi>Guard,</hi> The firſt which preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are.
<note place="margin">100 Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Le Cent Gentils hommes,</hi> ſo named from their primary reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (albeit now double in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) they are called the Kings Company, and wait on him upon all days of Ceremony, and like occaſions.
<note place="margin">Muſquetiers on horsback</note> Next</p>
            <p>The <hi>Muſquetiers on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back,</hi> which during the <hi>Regency</hi> have been diſſolved, but are now in great probability to be reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the King: they were compoſed of a hundred and fifty horſemen, choſen out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the prime youth of the chiefeſt families of <hi>France,</hi> and at the firſt inſtituted by <hi>Lewis the thirteenth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Late Kings curioſity in chooſing them.</note> father of this preſent King, who was ſo <hi>Phyſiognomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169778:38"/>punctual in their Election, that it is reported, he would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit none who were of a Red hair: Theſe waited on his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie in Perſon when ever hee went abroad: but after theſe, and the more Ancient farr (who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their immediate attendance on the Perſon of the King wee are to accompt as principall and ſolid Forces of the State) are the <hi>Guards of French, Scotch, and Swiſſe:</hi> Of all whom, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe who approach neereſt to the perſon of his Majeſty are the <hi>Scotch</hi> (by an extraordinary &amp; ſpecial good fortune (it ſeems) ever eſteemed faithfull to this King and Crown only, for they are very neer his perſon, and therefore called the <hi>Guard de La Manch</hi>) I will firſt begin with them.
<note place="margin">Scotchguard or guard de la Manch.</note> They conſiſt of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Archers,</hi> and four <hi>Exempts,</hi> who carry a <hi>ſtaffe</hi> or Trunche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſtead of an <hi>halberd,</hi> with the reſt, from whence they are ſo denominated: Theſe wait
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169778:39"/>on the King, and obſerve him in all motions, joyned alſo with ſome other of his Majeſties guards, wherof ſome bear halberds, others Carabines, whether the King be at Table, in Coach, or in his bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber. But this guard of <hi>Scots,</hi> as ſympathizing with the calamity of their Nation, is of late years very much impaired, divers French ſuborned in their places,
<note place="margin">Decay of the Scots at preſent.</note> and many of their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges loſt and infringed, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it ſeems at preſent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain rather a name then a real Being.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Swiſſe</hi> (for being likewiſe ſtrangers) I produce in the next place:
<note place="margin">Guard of Swiſſe.</note> The guard of this grim Nation, is compoſed of <hi>ſixteen Companies:</hi> but of theſe the more immediately attending as the Kings conſtant Guard are only an hundred of them, who all weare the Kings cloath, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which halberds on their ſhoulders, drum always beating, and fife playing before his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169778:39"/>when'ere he ſtirs but into the City.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the <hi>Guard of French,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Guard of F. or Regiment des Guards.</note> called the <hi>Regiment des Guards,</hi> with the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> (compoſing two entire Companies) guard all the avenues and precincts of the <hi>Kings Palace:</hi> They are both of them two Regiments, whereof each is made up of 30 companies, conſiſting of two hundred men a piece, if full; and Beſides theſe there is alſo another <hi>Companie de Gens d' Armes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gens d'arms Cavalry.</note> who are <hi>Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieres,</hi> &amp; ſerve quarterly on horſe back.</p>
            <p>Thus is this great <hi>Monarch</hi> ſo inviron'd with men of iron whereever he goes, that one who ſhould meet him abroad, though but upon the moſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary occaſion, would ſuppoſe them an Army Marching rather to defend or invade ſome diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Province, then the private guard only of a Princes Perſon; ſo carefull have the Kings of <hi>France</hi> ever been to maintain this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169778:40"/>principle of greatneſſe and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the very <hi>quinteſſence</hi> certainly of true Polity,
<note place="margin">True ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar hy.</note> and infallibleſt ſignatures of an abſolute juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>It would now peradventure be thought proper here to ſpeak next of the <hi>Militia,</hi> having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready placed the <hi>Guards,</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed compoſe ſo conſiderable a part thereof: but becauſe wee have now done with the court,
<note place="margin">Officers of State.</note> we will in the next caſt our eyes upon the State, and afterwards ſecure it.</p>
            <p>But firſt a word or two tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Kings <hi>Revenue,</hi> &amp; <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ks Revenue</note> as being the very Nerves and Pillars of all earthly gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur.</p>
            <p>The ordinary <hi>Revenue</hi> of the Kings of <hi>France</hi> is extreamly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, albeit vaſtly augmented within theſe late few years, and (beſides from the <hi>Domains</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly engaged to the Crowne) are infinitely increaſed by the <hi>Doüanes Tailles,</hi> and other <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:169778:40"/>ariſing upon all manner of Merchandize; a treaſure alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether uncertain, and therefore impoſed ſtill as occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and at the pleaſure of the King. In order to this, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed ſeverall <hi>grand Officers</hi> of whom in order firſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Superintendent of the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Superinten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent des Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or Cuoſtumes.</note> equivalent to our <hi>quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> Lord <hi>High Treaſurer,</hi> and officers depending on him. This is he who doth abſolutely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the <hi>Farmes</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the King, hath the charge and diſpenſation of the <hi>Revenues:</hi> In ſhort, it is a place ſo immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly lucrative, and prodigiouſly rich, (as being obnoxious to no Account) that there is no man able to make a juſt eſtimate of their gaine. Subordinate to him are <hi>four other Intendents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Threſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiers de l' Eſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne.</note> and as many <hi>Treaſurers de l' Eſpargne,</hi> whereof one of each wait every moneth, and theſe are thoſe great <hi>Financiers,</hi> who ſuck the very bloud of the people; for
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169778:41"/>which (like the <hi>Jewiſh Publicani</hi> their <hi>Brethren</hi>) they are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently blaſphemed by them upon all occaſions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Treſoriers de l' Eſpargne</hi> (which are as Chancellours of the Exchequer have an alterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive office; becauſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them is not alwayes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, places of that vaſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, that they are frequently ſold at no leſſe then a million of livers: for this the <hi>Eſpargne</hi> is reſembled to the Ocean ſea, into which, like ſo many rivers, all the other <hi>Receipts,</hi> generall and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, of the Kings Revenue, do praecipitate themſelves, and pay their tribute. From hence all other the <hi>Treaſures,</hi> as well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary as extraordinary, of the <hi>Wars, Generals of the Provinces, Maritime Officers,</hi> Payers of <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick rents, Courts, &amp;c.</hi> receive money, and advance for their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral and reſpective diſtributions.</p>
            <p>There are likewiſe beſides theſe, the Treaſurers of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169778:41"/>Caſuelles,</hi> who are four.
<note place="margin">The Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the parties Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuelles.</note> Theſe have charge to receive all monies proceeding from the ſale of offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (which is a gain here openly avowed.) But that which much countervails the inconvenience of their caſualties, unto which they are incident, is, that though a man depoſit a vaſt ſumme, and even exhauſt himſelfe for the purchace, they are yet hereditary,
<note place="margin">Caſual Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary even to Widows, and how.</note> ſo that even the <hi>Widow</hi> of the defunct, may delegate it to a Deputy, or <hi>Proxy,</hi> the King on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſerving a ſmall annuall rent, which they call <hi>La Paulet;</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of which payment, or that the perſon die without having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned his office. Theſe Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers diſpoſe of it to the Kings uſe and benefit.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Controuler General des Finances,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Comptrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers General of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</note> his office it is to regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter all receipts and expences; but for the preſent, it remaines extinct.</p>
            <p>Theſe Treaſurers are diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Generalities</hi> or <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aux</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bureaux &amp; Generalties</note>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:169778:42"/>(ſo called from a ſtuff of that name which covereth the table,
<note place="margin">Bureaux and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralties.</note> as our Exchequer) the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralties are twenty two great Cities, and each of thoſe have their generall and particular <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers,</hi> which laſt bring the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of <hi>Tailles</hi> (which certain elected officers impoſe or aſſeſſe upon the Pariſhes) unto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective <hi>Collectors</hi> who receive it:
<note place="margin">How the taxes are collected.</note> and theſe at <hi>Paris</hi> render it into the Office aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The ancient Kings of <hi>France</hi> had other wayes then theſe to ſubſiſt,
<note place="margin">Kings of France had other wayes of ſubſiſting till King Pepin.</note> till <hi>Pepin</hi> and ſome later Princes of the third Line, ſo much augmented the <hi>Domaine</hi> of the Crown; as by <hi>Appanages,</hi> which through defect of Iſſue Male now revert unto it; alſo by poſſeſſion of Lands and <hi>Seignio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> annexed to the <hi>Crown,</hi> by <hi>Rents, Fifts,</hi> and other rights proceeding from <hi>Fiefs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Impoſitions by Edicts.</note> By <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions</hi> and dues which are pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by <hi>Edicts.</hi> By a number of Lands who owe faith, and do <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:169778:42"/>to the Prince.
<note place="margin">Droict d' Aubaine, death of ſtrangers, Baſtardy, Vacancy through death, Firſt-fruits and dues from Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks.</note> By the <hi>Droct d' Aubaine,</hi> by which the goods of ſtrangers dying in <hi>France,</hi> moſt inhoſpitality eſcheat to the King; putting (in this reſpect) no difference between them, and <hi>Baſtards</hi> unnaturalized. By the goods vacant through death, &amp;c. By <hi>Annates</hi> or Firſt fruits, Dues from certain <hi>Archbiſhopricks</hi> and <hi>Biſhopricks,</hi> to the number of 30, and more: as likewiſe innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable other wayes, which here it were too long to reckon up.</p>
            <p>Nor can the <hi>Domain</hi> be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alienated, then (as already hath been ſaid) in caſe of <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panages:</hi> The other upon ſome extraordinary and deſperate ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as in occaſion of warre, yet then alſo but upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Redemption,</hi> and that they be both firſt <hi>verified</hi> in Parliament. But theſe it ſeems of late, not ſufficing the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick expenſes of ſo great a Prince and his many Armies; Thoſe <hi>Tailles</hi> and ſubſidiary aſſiſtances
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169778:43"/>before mentioned, have been more frequently levied;
<note place="margin">The ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Souldiery.</note> yea now (ſince <hi>Charles the ſeventh</hi>) made the Ordinary Entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Souldiery.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the <hi>Gentry and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> (for theſe tearms are coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and convertible in France) <hi>Churchmen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gentry and Clergy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes.</note> and their <hi>dependants</hi> are exempt from theſe contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; an immunity which they enjoy as a diſtinction, which ours of the ſame quality in <hi>England</hi> never ſo much as taſted off; ſo that (amongſt us) if a perſon be not <hi>Rich,</hi> let him be never ſo well borne,
<note place="margin">Nobility no advantage in England.</note> the <hi>Peaſant</hi> is as good a man every whit for any priviledg which the other enjoys above him; through which defect, as there remains little encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reward for ancient vertue or future induſtry, ſo muſt it needs, in time both utterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, and degenerate the race of the moſt illuſtrious Families, which have yet hitherto remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:169778:43"/>
            <p>The <hi>Aides</hi> (which <hi>I</hi> therefore the rather mention,
<note place="margin">The Aid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, what, and when inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted.</note> becauſe it was inſtituted upon occaſion of King <hi>John's</hi> impriſonment in <hi>England</hi>) is now become a perpetual and generall <hi>Tax</hi> upon all ſorts of Commodities whatever,
<note place="margin">All commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in France, wheat onely exempted.</note> excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>wheat</hi> only, which is the ſole individual in all <hi>France</hi> free from any Impoſt.</p>
            <p>But that which ſeaſons all the reſt, and is indeed a principal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient to the Kings Vaſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, is the <hi>Gabels</hi> upon <hi>Salt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gabels up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Salt.</note> which yeelds this Monarch more then <hi>Twenty Millions of Livers:</hi> for which reſpect there are divers officers appertaining therto, ſome whereof have power to conſtrain men to buy a certain quantity of the King whether they wil or no;
<note place="margin">Rigour of exacting.</note> a rigour, ſome interpret extreamly approaching the very height of extortion: ſome particular pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces yet of the Kingdome, (as to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Frontiers, and ſea towns) are exempted, and have their ſalt quit of any impoſt at all.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:169778:44"/>
            <p>Theſe are in fine the moſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall quarries <hi>from</hi> whence this <hi>Monarch</hi> diggs forth and fetches his treaſure and revenue,
<note place="margin">K. of Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces's Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue 14 mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> which thoſe who are yet thought to have made a favourable <hi>Audite,</hi> do not bluſh to affirm, ammounts unto more then <hi>an hundred and fourty Millions of Livers,</hi> which is about <hi>fourteen Millions of our mony:</hi> nay ſome, that in <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Richlieus</hi> time, it was brought to an <hi>hundred and fifty:</hi> which portentous and monſtrous Treaſure, together with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement and manner of exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting it, might (as ſome think) ſerve a little to extenuate that which was yet thought a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion too large for a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent prince, whoſe whole Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue could never yet be ſtretched to above one <hi>Million ſterling</hi> in all, <hi>viis et modis.</hi> Which is ſome thirteen ſhort of that, which the <hi>Kings of France</hi> at preſent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy.</p>
            <p>Now 'ere we define the more
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169778:44"/>diſtinct <hi>Miniſters of State,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Supream counſels of France.</note> wee wil firſt ſpeak ſeverally of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream <hi>Counſels</hi> which are two: The chief is called the <hi>ſecret</hi> or (more frequently) <hi>le Conſeil d'en hault,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">Le Counſel d'en hault, of this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel are the Duke of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans, Prince of Condé; The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and 4 principall Secretaries of State.</note> (after our old En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh ſtile) the <hi>Cabinet Counſel;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is commonly held in the Kings <hi>Bedchamber:</hi> for which reſpect you may reaſonably imagine it to be compoſed but of few, and thoſe the prime and moſt illuſtrious perſons of charge and title in the Kingdome: ſo that (according to the nature of affaires) it is ſometimes reduced unto two or three only: but upon intelligences and tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>State,</hi> as thoſe which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern matter of <hi>warr, forrain Alliances,</hi> &amp;c. Then there is a fuller number of other <hi>Miniſters</hi> required to be preſent.</p>
            <p>The other Conſeil is termed <hi>le Conſeil d'Eſtat &amp; privé</hi> where,
<note place="margin">The counſel of State.</note> when the King himſelf ſits not, the <hi>Precedency</hi> is given to the firſt <hi>Prince of the Blood then preſent,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:169778:45"/>and in default of their abſence, to the <hi>Chancelour,</hi> who, together with the <hi>Treaſurer</hi> or <hi>Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendent,</hi> hath principal authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in all thoſe Courts I have, or ſhall ſpeak of; and this <hi>Court</hi> (beſides the above named who are chief) is compoſed of many <hi>Counſellours of State,</hi> who are all perſons of great merit, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſuch as have given ſignal teſtimonies of their abilities and addreſſe by their long ſervices, as <hi>Ambaſſadors and Orators</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Princes; or <hi>officers</hi> in other <hi>juriſdictions</hi> and <hi>Counſels:</hi> alſo to this <hi>Court</hi> appertaine foure <hi>Secretaries</hi> that ſerve quarterly: eighteen <hi>Maiſtres de Requeſts,</hi> who (according to the nature of the affaire) with the Intendents, make the <hi>Reports,</hi> having firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved the buſineſſe amongſt themſelves, according to which the <hi>Arreſt</hi> is ſometimes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Counſell</hi> paſſe all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters belonging either to <hi>Warr</hi> or
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169778:45"/>
               <hi>Peace,</hi> and all other concerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Crown</hi> whatever; for here they determine <hi>definitively,</hi> which judgment ſo paſſed, is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med an <hi>Arreſt</hi> or <hi>Act of Councell;</hi> howbeit, in cauſes of high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence they are often revoked both from <hi>this Tribunall</hi> (yea, and the <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf alſo) unto the <hi>Counſeil d'-en-hault</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a Counſell but of a later <hi>Initiation.</hi> Branches from this are alſo the Counſell of the <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> or Cuſtomes, called the <hi>Councel of direction;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> where all the affaires of the <hi>Exchequer</hi> are diſpoſed: likewiſe the <hi>Chancelor</hi> holdeth another Counſell,
<note place="margin">The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> called the <hi>Counſeil des parties,</hi> wherein the <hi>Proceſſes</hi> of particular parties and <hi>Recuſations</hi> have their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hearing; and to this alſo belong quarterly <hi>Secretaries</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</p>
            <p>Now the manner of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in theſe <hi>Courts</hi> goes according to the diſpoſition of the ſeverall affairs,
<note place="margin">The manner of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in theſe Courts.</note> by the <hi>Reports</hi> made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169778:46"/>
               <hi>reformed</hi> and firſt ſigned, which is by <hi>them,</hi> then by the <hi>Chancellor</hi> if it be at the <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of parties;</hi> if at the <hi>Finances,</hi> by the <hi>Duke of Orleans, Monſ<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, the Prince,</hi> and <hi>Superintendents,</hi> who deliver them to the <hi>Grefier</hi> or Clerk, by whom they are to be allowed, that is <hi>paragraphed</hi> in Parchment, to which they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyne a <hi>commiſſion</hi> which is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the <hi>chancellor,</hi> if they are to be immediately executed. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Arreſts</hi> and Acts of Counſel are executed by an <hi>uſher</hi> or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaent of the Counſel, who wears a chaine of Gold about his neck, with a <hi>Medail</hi> pendent, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is impreſſed the Kings pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.
<note place="margin">Grand Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeil.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There is likewiſe another <hi>Councell,</hi> called the <hi>Grand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeil,</hi> in which alſo the <hi>Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> preſides virtually, though ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom preſent in perſon; and this is Compoſed of four <hi>Preſidents,</hi> and a hundred and fifty Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, who ſerve by <hi>Semeſter:</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:169778:46"/>and this <hi>court</hi> is chiefly, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed only converſant in affaires <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> ſuch as concerne <hi>Biſhopricks, Priories, Hoſpitals,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>collation</hi> and <hi>preſentation</hi> to Benefices in the juriſdiction ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> within this Realme; and therefore here is the <hi>Kings</hi> Advocate, and <hi>proctor Generall</hi> continually attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>And now (returning to our former diviſion) we may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that the more ancient officers of the <hi>Crown</hi> were likewiſe three: viz. The <hi>Conneſtable,</hi> the <hi>Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal</hi> and the <hi>Chancellor:</hi> I ſhall forbear a while to ſpeak much of the two firſt, till I come to treat particularly concerning matters of warr:
<note place="margin">Officers of State &amp; Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. Chancelour of France.</note> we are now in affaires of <hi>State</hi> and Juſtice, wherein this laſt in our diviſion as chiefe and ſoveraign; his office is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch and modifie all the <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>gifts</hi> of the King, is <hi>keeper</hi> of the <hi>Great ſeale,</hi> with which hee confirmes all the <hi>Ordinances, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169778:47"/>declarations</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> of his Majeſty; for which reſpect he hath in <hi>Parliament</hi> his ſeat on the left hand of the King, when he is there preſent. But there are no dayes properly deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>ſealing,</hi> that wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon the will of the <hi>Chancellour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Days and manner of Sealing.</note> The manner thereof is this: The <hi>chancellour</hi> ſits at the middle of a large Table, upon which is placed a <hi>cabinet</hi> or coffer (wherein there is locked all the publick <hi>ſeals</hi> of France) the key of which he carries about his neck: at the End of this Table are two <hi>Maſters of Requeſts,</hi> with whom he may adviſe in caſe the affaire require it; and over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Chancelor</hi> one of the four <hi>Referendaries</hi> of France who reads all the <hi>Letters, Arreſts,</hi> and other expeditions, which if ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, are accommodated with <hi>Yellow wax</hi> fitting and ready for the ſeale, and ſo put up into a box to be controuled by the <hi>Kings Secretaries,</hi> who muſt firſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169778:47"/>allow and <hi>Paragraph</hi> them, and then they are ſealed: for <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> of higheſt conſequence, as <hi>Treaties, Edicts, Abolitions,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>green wax:</hi> but the ſeals of <hi>Dauphine</hi> are in <hi>red:</hi> Moreover the <hi>character</hi> of the <hi>Chancelor</hi> is eſteemed ſo ſacred &amp; Inviolable, that it remains altogether indele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but by <hi>death</hi> onely;
<note place="margin">Guard des ſceaux.</note> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding upon decadency, or diſgrace with the King, there is commonly one called <hi>Gard des Sceaux,</hi> who executeth his charg &amp; hath alſo the ſame authority; for the <hi>Seales</hi> may be taken away at his Majeſties pleaſure, but not the <hi>Chancelorſhip,</hi> which as it is never to dye, but with his Perſon, ſo may he not put on <hi>Mourning</hi> for the <hi>King himſelf,</hi> his <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Mother</hi> if any of them deceaſe, as being inſenſible of all other <hi>Relations,</hi> and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations beſides the ſole intereſt of the <hi>People:</hi> his habite is a Robe of <hi>black Velvet</hi> doubled, or lined with Crimſon pluſh: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169778:48"/>him goe two <hi>Searjeants,</hi> with chains of Gold, who bear 2 rich <hi>maces</hi> of gold on their ſhoulders.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Secretaries of State</hi> and commands of the King are <hi>four</hi> in number;
<note place="margin">Secretaries of State.</note> whoſe functions, for being different, deſerve to bee mentioned in the next place. One of theſe Secretaries is for Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions altogether <hi>forraign:</hi> one for affaires <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices; a third for matters only appertaining to the <hi>Kings houſe,</hi> and the fourth, ſerves for affairs and concernements of <hi>war;</hi> and thus have they the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſo <hi>cantoniz'd</hi> betwixt them, that upon all particular Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences of the <hi>Provinces,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one knows his diviſion: In <hi>Court</hi> and preſence of the King, they waite alternatively by <hi>Months;</hi> for he uſes them likewiſe in affaires of the <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet,</hi> which for not being mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of State, hee will not have made known or divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:169778:48"/>
            <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">Maſters of Requeſts.</note> The <hi>Maſters of Requeſt</hi> (of whom there are at preſent no leſſe then ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) are as it were <hi>Aſſeſſors</hi> of the <hi>Chancellour,</hi> and compoſe the body of the Court of <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,</hi> (of which we ſhall ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeak) and have their Seats next to the <hi>Counſellers,</hi> but not exceeding four at a time. In abſence of the <hi>Preſidents,</hi> they preſide alſo in many other <hi>Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catures,</hi> and <hi>Bailliages:</hi> theſe make report and ſign the <hi>Requeſt of Juſtice,</hi> and ſometimes the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the <hi>Exchequer:</hi> they are likewiſe many times choſen for <hi>Extraordinary Embaſſades,</hi> as wel as Commiſſioners for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in the Cities and Provinces, where they judg and determine upon all affairs of the Crowne with moſt abſolute power and authority.</p>
            <p>The reſt of the Officers more immediately belonging to the Kings Revenue I have touched at large already. I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169778:49"/>come now to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of France,</hi> of whom there hath hitherto been ſo much talke.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Juſtice of France</hi> (in the equal diſpenſation whereof ſhould be the glory and diadem of a Prince in Peace,
<note place="margin">Parliament of France,</note> as is the multitude of people his viſible ſtrength in warr) is doubtleſſe very good, but wonderfully ill executed; which happens through the ſordid corruption of ſuch as diſpenſe it for mony and favour, without which there is nothing to be hoped for in this <hi>Kingdom:</hi> and good reaſon there ſhould bee ſome gaine made of that which the dividers thereof buy ſo dear, purchaſing their places and offices at ſuch exceſſive charges, that they are conſtrained to fell their Vertue to him who bidds moſt for it. But this is not (I ſuppoſe) the only Monopoly which drives that trade.
<note place="margin">by whom e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip the Faire</hi> eſtabliſhed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169778:49"/>the <hi>Parliament of Paris;</hi> for before it was <hi>Ambulatory,</hi> and onely obſerved the motion of the King) whither both <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks</hi> and <hi>ſeculars</hi> repaired. As it is now conſtituted, it is compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of <hi>Five houſes</hi> or chambers: <hi>La Grand Chambre</hi> hath twenty five <hi>Counſellers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">La grand chambre des Enqueſts.</note> who take cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance of affairs of higheſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence: and of five <hi>Chambres des Enqueſts,</hi> to either of which there is alſo about the ſame num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Counſellers:</hi> likewiſe two other Chambers, one whereof is called <hi>La Tournelle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">La Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelle.</note> wherein are pleaded only matters <hi>Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> compoſed of two Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours of the <hi>Grand Chambre,</hi> and of two of every <hi>Chambre des Enqueſts.</hi> The <hi>Chambre del' E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> that is of the <hi>Edict of Nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> which only toucheth the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo compoſed of two <hi>Counſellers,</hi> out of each of the ſix other Chambers, who are nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted every ſecond year by the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169778:50"/>
               <hi>Chancellour</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant deputy Generall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De l' Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſident au Mort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. becauſe there ſtandeth a cup <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ade in faſhion of a mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er over the mantling of the Arms in lieu of a wreath and helmet.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the great <hi>Chambre</hi> preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the <hi>Preſident au Mortier,</hi> who preſenteth the ancient <hi>Dukes</hi> and <hi>Peers:</hi> theſe <hi>preſidents</hi> are Counſellers of <hi>State</hi> the firſt day of their reception, and have about their neck an hood of vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, lined with furr, from whence ſome affirme they derive their name: they are now in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſeven or eight, having of late been encreaſed.</p>
            <p>To all the other <hi>Chambers of Parliament</hi> there are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Preſidents:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preſidents, Conſeillers, Advocats &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rocteurs.</note> viz. two at the <hi>Tournelle,</hi> and one at the <hi>Edict:</hi> To each <hi>Chambre des Enqueſts</hi> are two, but theſe laſt for being only <hi>commiſsionated Counſellers,</hi> have no places as <hi>preſidents</hi> in ful aſſemblies of <hi>Parliament.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>preſidents</hi> and Counſellers; there is moreover a <hi>Procureur,</hi> and two <hi>Advocates General,</hi> who intervene in all Cauſes which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern either the King or State:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169778:50"/>beſides an Infinity of other <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates</hi> who are rather to count by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>titudes then numbers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, only the <hi>proctors</hi> have of late years been reduced to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 600.</p>
            <p>There is likewiſe a <hi>Greffier en chef,</hi> or <hi>clerk of the Parliament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clerk of the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> one of the moſt luerative charges of <hi>France,</hi> as eſteemed to be no leſſe worth then an 100 Crowns of Gold a day: This office ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now ſucceſſively remained in the family of <hi>Monſieur, du Tillet</hi> neer three hundred years, we could not paſſe his name in ſilence; Laſtly, of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, Searjeants, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhers,</hi> and under officers there are in very great numbers.</p>
            <p>All the Officers of Parliament wear a long <hi>Gown,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs of the Officers of Parlia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and ſquare <hi>cap,</hi> but the <hi>Preſidents au Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier</hi> and <hi>Counſellours,</hi> upon ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn occaſions, put on Robes of <hi>ſcarlet,</hi> which are trimmed with black velvet.</p>
            <p>The Solemne <hi>Arreſts or Acts
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169778:51"/>of Parliament</hi> are pronounced four times the year:
<note place="margin">Arreſts of Parl. when pronounced.</note> viz. on <hi>Chriſtmas Eves eve,</hi> on the <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> before <hi>Eaſter,</hi> on <hi>Whitſon Eves eve,</hi> and the ſeventh day of <hi>Sept.</hi> till which, from the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row after the feaſt of St <hi>Martine it continues:</hi> but the <hi>Parliament</hi> doth not open untill ſuch time as the King renews their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>there are beſides <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Paris, that have parliaments</note> theſe nine Cities which have Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Toulouſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Roüen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Bourdeaux.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Dijon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Grenoble.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Aix.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Rheims.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Pau.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Mets.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſe Conſtitution and Compoſition are alike to that of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In what they differ from the Par. of Paris.</note> except that of <hi>Mets</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:169778:51"/>and <hi>Roüen,</hi> whoſe Preſident and Counſellers of late ſerve ſeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraly, that is half during one ſix months, and halfe the other: ſome of the Parliaments alſo have no chamber of <hi>Edict,</hi> as <hi>Rheims,</hi> and <hi>Dijon,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of thoſe parts repaire to <hi>Paris</hi> to plead; and in <hi>Toulouſe, Bordeaux,</hi> and <hi>Grenoble,</hi> for default thereof, thoſe of the <hi>Religion</hi> have eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed them Chambers <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parties,</hi> that is, of equal num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Romaniſts;</hi> nor have the other <hi>Parliaments</hi> ſo many chambers of <hi>Enqueſts,</hi> as not (in truth) needing them</p>
            <p>Likewiſe this <hi>Prerogative</hi> hath the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prerogative of the P. of Paris.</note> that it hath the ſole honour to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Court of Peers;</hi> for here only can they of right be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: yet this <hi>priviledg</hi> was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to protect them, at what time the late great <hi>Cardinal de Richlieu</hi> made bold to infringe it, when it ſerved to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:169778:52"/>
            <p>In all theſe Parliaments afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid the <hi>Advocates</hi> plead covered,
<note place="margin">How the Advocates and proctors plead.</note> but the <hi>Prectors</hi> both <hi>bareheaded and kneeling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, the buſineſſe of the <hi>Parliament of Paris,</hi> beſides the <hi>verifying</hi> of the Kings <hi>Edicts, Ordinances, and letters Patents</hi> (as hath been already touched) is the diſpenſing of all other Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Criminall:</hi> here the <hi>Appanages</hi> of the crown are regulated, the erection of new <hi>dignities, Modification</hi> of the <hi>Popes Legats, Commiſſions,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedures to <hi>Baniſhment, Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of <hi>naturalty, Pardons</hi> and the like ſupream tranſactions of State have their genuine and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſource.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> have right of <hi>place,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biſhops and eccleſiaſticks in Parli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ament have place, no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberative Voice, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept B. of Paris, and abbot of St. Denys.</note> but no <hi>deliberative Voice,</hi> except only the <hi>Archbiſhop of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and <hi>Abbot of Saint De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys.</hi> Thus much ſhall ſuffice to have been ſpoken touching the <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:169778:52"/>
            <p>The <hi>Chamber of compts</hi> (which comes next in order) is a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction and <hi>Court</hi> apart,
<note place="margin">Chamber of compts, its high au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and number.</note> that concernes &amp; judges the accompt of all the <hi>Receivers, Treaſurers</hi> and <hi>officers</hi> paid into, or received out of he Kings <hi>Exchequers,</hi> for which cauſe all their <hi>Letters, Edicts, Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c. are read, regiſtred, and verified. Here it is that homage for <hi>Feifs</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from the <hi>Crown</hi> are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged. It hath belonging to it ten <hi>Preſidents, Monſieur Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas,</hi> who is the firſt (having from Father to Son conſerved this charge neer two hundred years in his Family) hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed for his charge 1400000 Livers, which the late <hi>D'Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> offered him for it. To it alſo appertaineth <hi>ſeventy Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres des compts, eighty Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors:</hi> in fine, it is a <hi>Court</hi> of that high Authority, that it hath ſometimes ſtood even in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with the Parliament it ſelf. There are eight of theſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169778:53"/>in France.
<note place="margin">Chambers des Requeſts du Palais.</note> Beſides this Court, there are likewiſe the two <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres des Requeſts du Palais,</hi> where is pleaded the Priviledg of the <hi>Royall offices,</hi> and houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; and therefore they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of Counſellers of <hi>parliament,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cour des Monnoyes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of three <hi>Preſidents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cour des Monnoyes.</note> twenty four <hi>Conſeillers,</hi> theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the <hi>Mint</hi> in all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.
<note place="margin">Mint.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo the Admiralty,
<note place="margin">Admiralty and Table de Marbre.</note> called the <hi>Table de Marbre</hi> inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for <hi>Maritime affaires.</hi> And laſtly,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Les Eaux &amp; Forreſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Waters and Forreſts.</note> with ſome other inferiour <hi>courts,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we have already ſufficiently ſpoken elſewhere.</p>
            <p>And ſo I am come out of <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi> to the other two of our three ancient <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers,</hi> viz. the <hi>Conneſtable</hi> and <hi>Mareſchall</hi> of France, being the laſt of our diviſion and will naturally lead us to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169778:53"/>diſcourſe ſomething of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Conneſtable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Military of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and firſt the Conneſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of F.</note> albeit an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, to a greater then which the <hi>King himſelf</hi> can promote no <hi>ſubject,</hi> yet for that it is not a charge which is always in being, but upon extraordinary Emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies and grand occaſions, will be needleſſe to ſay more of it, then that this Office holdeth ranke immediately after the <hi>Princes of the blood;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The D. of Orleans is as it were Conneſtable now.</note> and in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> it is before the <hi>Dukes</hi> and <hi>Pairs:</hi> The <hi>Conneſtable</hi> therefore is chief, ſuperiour, and <hi>Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſimo</hi> over the <hi>Armies</hi> of France, for which reſpect he hath his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction in the Court of the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble de Marbre;</hi> but at this day the <hi>Mareſchals</hi> ſupplying this high office (although pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſpeaking, but his <hi>Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants</hi>) come next to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of.
<note place="margin">Mareſchals de Fr.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Mareſchals de France,</hi> or rather, ſo many <hi>Generals,</hi> are the onely perſons of Enterpriſe and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169778:54"/>Action in their Armies, both at home and abroad; being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly men who are elevated to thoſe <hi>Charges,</hi> purely by their own Valour and Demerits: ſo that as their number is indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, ſo there is no Souldier, of what condition ſoever, but may poſſibly by his vertue aſpire to this preferment. I ſaid even now, that their Juriſdiction did much reſemble that of the <hi>Conneſtables;</hi> nor can they be deveſted of this honour during their lives. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe <hi>Mareſchals</hi> are deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined all matters of private quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels and defies incident to the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſe;</hi> for which cauſe they have their <hi>Provoſts</hi> or <hi>Lieutenants</hi> in all the greateſt Cities of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. They bear in their <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements</hi> a <hi>Truncheon Salter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe azure, ſemeéd with Flowr de lyces or.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally,
<note place="margin">Laſt diviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> (which is the laſt part of our diviſion) the three Modern Offices of the Crown, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Admiral of the French.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:169778:54"/>
               <item>2. <hi>Le Colonel de l' Infanterie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Le Grand Maiſtre de l'Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the firſt place the <hi>Admiral,</hi> (who holds likewiſe his place du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring life) is Generall of all the <hi>Kings forces</hi> by <hi>ſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Admirall.</note> and under him are al the <hi>Marine juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> The <hi>charge</hi> hath in times paſt been divided unto more, both <hi>Guyenne</hi> and <hi>Provence</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving enjoyed theirs apart: but the defunct <hi>Cardinall de Richlieu</hi> (who hath left this high office to his <hi>Nephew</hi>) united them all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one: his juriſdiction alſo is at the <hi>Table de Marbre,</hi> where (for being but ſubalternate judges) their places in Parliament is at the lower end. The charge is now in the perſon of the <hi>Queen Regent,</hi> ſome ſay, the <hi>Duke of Vendoſme:</hi> likewiſe the <hi>General des Galeres</hi> hath here his ſeate,
<note place="margin">General des Galeres.</note> which is a place of very notable gaine and Authority on the coaſts of the <hi>Mediterranean ſeas,</hi> where his <hi>Majeſties Gallies</hi> do
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169778:55"/>both harbour and ride.
<note place="margin">Colonel of the Infantry</note>
            </p>
            <p>Next is the Colonell of the <hi>French Infantery,</hi> which is a charge one of the moſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in all reſpects, of <hi>France,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for Gain, receiving <hi>eight ſolz</hi> every Muſter for every ſouldiers head his authority being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally over all the <hi>French-foot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maſters of the Camp.</note> and hath for his <hi>Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels</hi> the <hi>Maiſtres de Camp:</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his name iſſue all <hi>Ordinances of Warr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is likewiſe a Colonel <hi>General des Suiſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Colonel General des Suiſſes</note> who hath juriſdiction over all thoſe Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, as well thoſe of the <hi>Kings Guard,</hi> as thoſe who ſerve in the field and in the <hi>Gariſon;</hi> of which there are conſtantly about eight thouſand in this Dominion.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all,
<note place="margin">Grand Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre de l'Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> the <hi>Grand Maiſtre de l'Artillerie,</hi> which is a charge equal with a <hi>Mareſchall of France:</hi> under his tuition and conduct is the <hi>Arſenall of Paris,</hi> all the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non and Ammunition</hi> of warre in the Kingdome, for which cauſe he
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169778:55"/>hath his <hi>Lieutenants, Captains,</hi> and other officers belonging to the <hi>Carriages</hi> in great number: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this, he hath the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>five millions</hi> of Livers, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the arbitrary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of above eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Officers;</hi> of all which he is obliged to no particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt.
<note place="margin">Grand pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curde France Mr. of the Religion of Malta.</note>
            </p>
            <p>There is likewiſe the <hi>Grand Prieur de France,</hi> which for being a quality of high reputation is not to be pretermitted. The <hi>Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of <hi>the Religion</hi> and Order of <hi>Malta</hi> for the French being not leſſe worth then 10000 pounds yearly: his ordinary <hi>Reſidence</hi> is at the Temple, a quarter in the town of <hi>Paris</hi> as is that of ours in <hi>London</hi> ſo called.
<note place="margin">Counſell of War.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Councel of Warr</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly held in the <hi>Palace of the Duke of Orleans,</hi> as being <hi>Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant</hi> General of all the Kings Forces, and therefore little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote (as hath been ſaid) from the dignity and charge of high <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtable.</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:169778:56"/>Thus we have done with the <hi>Courts and Officers of France:</hi> now we will take a Proſpect of the <hi>Forces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>King of France</hi> hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly four <hi>Armies</hi> in field:
<note place="margin">Conſtant ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Fr.</note> viz. that of <hi>Flanders,</hi> of <hi>Germanie,</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> and that of <hi>Catalogna;</hi> wherein the <hi>King, Queen, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur, the Duke of Anjou, the Duke of Orleans, Princes of the Blood, and Mareſchals</hi> of France have their ſeverall and individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Companies,</hi> whoſe <hi>Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants</hi> enjoy many ſingular pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedencies above other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the <hi>Armies:</hi> All theſe conſiſt of well armed horſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>light horſe</hi> are at preſent commanded by the <hi>Master of the Camp.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Light horſe and other forces under continuall pay.</note> The King hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly under pay about <hi>a hundred and forty Cornets</hi> of cavalry diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted into 56 <hi>Regiments,</hi> beſides of <hi>Strangers twelve:</hi> Of <hi>Infantry</hi> the King hath two hundred and ten, whereof ſome <hi>Regiments</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:169778:56"/>have thirty Companies, and every company payed for eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men effective. Moreover, his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> hath divers Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſtrangers, whereof enough hath been ſaid in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Armada Naval</hi> may be compoſed of about <hi>twenty men of Warr,</hi> and as many Gallies;
<note place="margin">Armada Naval.</note> I have ſhewed you before how theſe Forces are payed, and therefore we will proceed to the <hi>Governours of the Provinces,</hi> as being likewiſe Men of <hi>Armes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Governours of Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> have their <hi>Commiſſions</hi> (which are ſimple and depending on the pleaſure of the King) <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Governours of prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nces, cities and ſorts.</note> where they have their <hi>ſeats</hi> next after the <hi>premiers preſidents:</hi> they are in ſome degree equivalent to our <hi>Lieutenants of the ſhire,</hi> but exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe a much more vigorous power, which is yet reſtrained to matters of <hi>Armes;</hi> for in other juſtice
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169778:57"/>they meddle not at all. So likewiſe the <hi>Governors of Cities, Fortreſſes,</hi> and places of ſtrength, all which are choſen of perſons of Blood, Valour and merit. But before we altogether quit this ſubject of Armes, it wil not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to ſay ſomthing here of the order of <hi>Knighthood in</hi> France.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not much amuſe you with thoſe <hi>orders</hi> which are ſo far antiquated,
<note place="margin">Orders of Chevalrie in France.</note> that even the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralds themſelves can ſcarcely ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us any certain accompt: Such is that which is named <hi>de la Genette,</hi> Inſtituted by <hi>Charls Martel,</hi> or the Order <hi>de l'Eſtoile</hi> by King <hi>John,</hi> the Order of the <hi>Croiſant, Porc Eſpic,</hi> nor much concerning the order of Saint <hi>Michael</hi> it ſelf,
<note place="margin">Inſtituted 1469 by Lewis the eleventh.</note> although not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages ſince firſt inſtituted, and for a long while, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Order in the Kingdome; compoſed but of 36, becauſe (as the manner of this <hi>Nation</hi> is to be as ſoon weary of their new inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as children are of Rattles)
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169778:57"/>they begin to have this Order al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in contempt,
<note place="margin">Ordre de S. Michael.</note> albeit the chain and pendent badg be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly reſerved in the <hi>Coat Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,</hi> together with that which is now in Vogue, and next enſues.
<note place="margin">Ordre du <hi>S.</hi> Eſprit. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>L'Ordre du S. Eſprit</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted on <hi>new years Day, Anno</hi> 1579, <hi>by Henry the third,</hi> and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with that name, becauſe he was both born, and afterwards Elected <hi>King of Polonia</hi> on <hi>Whitſonday:</hi> This Prince reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the number alſo to thirty ſix; but that is likewiſe as indefinite as it pleaſes the King: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it remaines yet the <hi>Order</hi> of greateſt eſteem, and therefore let us look a while upon the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the <hi>Inauguration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The day of their <hi>Reception</hi> they appear all in <hi>Cloath of ſilver,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reception.</note> their cloaks (eſpecially the capes) cut <hi>a l'antique,</hi> of black velvet; which they put off and change, to receive on them a robe of <hi>green</hi> Velvet ful of Embroydred <hi>tongues of fire:</hi> then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining on their knees, the King
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169778:58"/>hands between the palmes of his own, ſtriking them lightly upon the ſhoulder, and <hi>kiſſes</hi> their Cheeke.</p>
            <p>Ordinarily they wear a Flame,
<note place="margin">Order.</note> or Orange colour Croſſe of vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet upon the left ſide of their cloakes, in the midſt whereof is emboſted a <hi>dove</hi> of ſilver, and about it a glory of Rayes, like that which our Knights of the Garter in England do wear, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt aſſumed that <hi>mode</hi> from the <hi>French,</hi> albeit for Antiquity of the <hi>Order,</hi> ours ſtands much before it.</p>
            <p>About their bodies likewiſe they wear a <hi>blew ribbon</hi> which of late they have <hi>watered,</hi> and at the end of that a <hi>Croſſe of Gold</hi> in the midſt whereof there is enna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mailed a <hi>White Dove:</hi> and this is all which I finde obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>We have been hitherto very ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of the <hi>State Eccleſiaſtick</hi> in particular,
<note place="margin">State Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchical.</note> which although it come laſt in <hi>Order,</hi> yet was it one
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169778:58"/>of the firſt in mine <hi>intention,</hi> as conſiſting of <hi>Perſons</hi> who beſides their qualities both for Extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and <hi>Letters,</hi> poſſeſſe alone one third part of the total Revenue of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Arch Biſhops</hi> of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are in number fifteen,
<note place="margin">Archbiſhops &amp; Biſhops.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he of <hi>Lyons</hi> is the <hi>Primate</hi> and <hi>Metropolitan,</hi> and ſome of theſe be <hi>Peers. Biſhopricks,</hi> two hundred and one.</p>
            <p>Of this <hi>Hierarchy</hi> is compoſed <hi>l' Egliſe Gallicane,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L'Egliſe Gallicane.</note> which by the <hi>concordats</hi> made with the <hi>Pope,</hi> hath ſundry rights and priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges extraordinary, which for that they are not much incident to our diſcourſe, we will purpoſely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and content our ſelves with what hath been briefly ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Having thus, as I was able, finiſhed my <hi>deſigne</hi> and your <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt,</hi> with what ſuccinctneſſe &amp; perſpicuity I might (for herein I am obliged to ſome <hi>Relations,</hi> more diſcourſes, and a little expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience)
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169778:59"/>I will make bold (the better to let you underſtand the full nature of things as they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and are govern'd at preſent) to reaſſume the <hi>Argument,</hi> &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver you the beſt and more ſolid opinions of men concerning the particulars already ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Government of France</hi> doth at preſent rather totter then ſtand upon the late great <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals</hi> ſubſtruction;
<note place="margin">Preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of France.</note>
               <note place="margin">Q. Regent.</note> the <hi>Queen Regent</hi> having ever ſince his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe continued in the principall miniſtry of State affairs:
<note place="margin">Card. Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tini.</note> Her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite <hi>Mazarini,</hi> a perſon of (to ſpeak with the world) farre greater fortune, then either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction or vertue; however he hath ſteered this great veſſel of Monarchy a long time, and that amidſt ſo many ſtormes, and in ſuch foul weather, as whether his craft or courage exceeds it is not yet decided: certaine it is, that as he hath longer held in, then by ſome wiſe men it was judg'd he could, ſo ſome late acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169778:59"/>of his (interpreted to have been ingratefull enough) make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thersdaily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fident of his abſolute ruine: and in truth, he doth play ſo hazardous a game at preſent, that as the hand is univerſally turned, it were great odds to lay on Confuſions ſide, ſo prodigious a fatality now threatning <hi>Princes,</hi> that if <hi>France</hi> compoſe not ſudden<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, theſe calamities I am confident, will <hi>epidemically</hi> viſite <hi>Europe</hi> for a time. And why it ſhould be that this active <hi>Nation</hi> have endured ſo many <hi>Strangers</hi> to governe them thus in cheif,
<note place="margin">Government by ſtrangers incident to this monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie.</note> I am much to ſeek for a reaſon, when I ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily behold the univerſal prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Nobleſſe;</hi> unleſſe peradventure to avoid emulation at <hi>Court</hi> 'twixt ſo many greater Princes and Subjects, as might elſe pretend to higheſt Authority, they rather ſubmit themſelves to the meaneſt <hi>Alien.</hi> But this by way of <hi>gloſſe</hi> and <hi>ſpecies,</hi> not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. The ſubtill have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been too hard for the ſimple:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169778:60"/>and though the law deny women ſucceſſion to the Crown, yet the Fate of the kingdome, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes of the ſex, furniſh'd them a title which hath fully recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for that injury.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Nobleſſe</hi> of <hi>France</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the <hi>Gentry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nobleſſe of France, and Gentry the ſame thing.</note> under one and the ſame common term; nor indeed is there in any <hi>Kingdome</hi> (ſave ours onely) that ſevere di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of <hi>Minores</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jores</hi> amongſt the <hi>Nobility:</hi> a difference which ſome think nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuits with true policy or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. But quitting this deciſion to whom it belongs, we are (as I ſaid) in this <hi>Dominion</hi> to take, the <hi>Nobleſſe</hi> (that is the <hi>Gentry</hi>) for the ſole viſible body, and conſequently the <hi>Plebeians</hi> of a far more vile,
<note place="margin">Plebeians, their miſery.</note> and naturally ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh genius, then they really are in any part of <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; which meanneſſe of ſpirit I eaſily conjecture to have been long ſince contracted from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeverity and liberty of their
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169778:60"/>Superiors; their incomparable paucity, and exceſſive oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>Other <hi>immunities,</hi> beſides the fore rehearſed, which the <hi>Nobleſs</hi> enjoy in <hi>France,</hi> is, that with their <hi>Penſions</hi> and <hi>Governments,</hi> they are likewiſe exempted from all <hi>Contributions</hi> upon their own <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains;</hi> which doth ſo far oblige them to their <hi>Prince,</hi> that there are none which render him ſuch real and conſiderable ſervice, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all urgent and brisk occaſions,
<note place="margin">Service the Nob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lity of France <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eld their Prince. Ban and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Ban.</note> as do the <hi>Gentry;</hi> eſpecially, at what time the <hi>Ban</hi> and <hi>Arrier-Ban</hi> be ſummoned to their ſeveral aſſignations: And to this He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roique life of the <hi>Field,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chevalry, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> they are generally addicted, as being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to excellently diſciplined from their very <hi>Cradles;</hi> by which means, certainly they become the beſt eſteemed, and moſt adroict <hi>Cavalry of Europe;</hi> nor doth this early education of them <hi>abroad,</hi> prejudice the State at home; for being kept, and diſſevered from projecting of commotion in the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:169778:61"/>
               <hi>Country,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rebellions for the moſt part impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous in France; and why?</note> their <hi>Rebellions</hi> have been for the moſt part, though fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, yet improſperous, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a party ever remaining with the <hi>Prince,</hi> whoſe perſonal preſence with them in the <hi>Field,</hi> gives an extraordinary life, and loyalty to their Actions.</p>
            <p>As touching the <hi>Plebeians</hi> or <hi>Roturiers</hi> of <hi>France;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Commons, their liti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gious nature in France.</note> truly I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem them for the moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble object, that one may likely behold upon the face of the Earth; eſpecially, thoſe which live towards the <hi>Frontiers,</hi> ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurably exhauſted by <hi>Taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Gabels, Impoſitions, Spoyls,</hi> and <hi>Contributions,</hi> unto which they are generally obnoxious: The reſt of the <hi>two firſt Eſtates,</hi> together with al their dependants, living onely upon their <hi>Revenues,</hi> remain free and exempt; but that which addes not a little to their <hi>Ruine,</hi> is (for all this) their extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <hi>litigious nature,</hi> and <hi>vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative diſpoſition,</hi> eſpecially thoſe of <hi>Normandy, Bretagne, Gaſcogny,</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:169778:61"/>and <hi>Provence;</hi> ſo that, what with the premiſes, delay of their <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,</hi> and the abominable corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> this rank of people ſeldom or never arrive to any conſiderable Fortune or Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, by their own wit or indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, as do ſo many of our <hi>Yeomen</hi> and <hi>Farmers</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Farmers in England.</note> By theſe means alſo, their ſpirits becoming ſo abjectly debaſed, they are not able to afford their <hi>Prince</hi> that ready ſervice in matter of <hi>Arms,</hi> as indeed their multitudes and neceſſities, both promiſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: To ſupply which defect, in all <hi>Expeditions of Conſequence,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> makes uſe of the <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> and <hi>Biſcaians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auxiliaries in the French Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> who being bred about the Confines and Frontiers of <hi>Spain,</hi> are much the better Soldiers, and eſteemed for the beſt <hi>Infantry</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> as alſo of the <hi>Dutch, Scotch, Iriſh, Italian,</hi> and others, in whom, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Suiſſe</hi> (a moſt principal Ingredient) conſiſteth their greateſt <hi>Foot confidence;</hi> the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169778:62"/>more conſiderable part, whereof being <hi>mercenary Auxiliaries,</hi> and very frequently left in great arrears, might peradventure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter to <hi>Politicians</hi> ſufficient cauſe of ſuſpition and diſcourſe; but the event having hitherto, for many ages paſt, been nothing prejudicial, takes away any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion of diſpute.</p>
            <p>The <hi>People of Trade</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niques of France.</note> are nothing ſo contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible as the <hi>commonſort,</hi> of whom we have ſpoken a little; many of them living very decently and handſomly in their houſes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the better ſort of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Merchants.</note> who are better furniſhed then the reſt; howbeit, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with our <hi>Country-men</hi> of the ſame <hi>quality,</hi> to be eſteemed, in truth, but as mean <hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks,</hi> and inconſiderable <hi>Pedlers.</hi> Thoſe of greateſt Wealth and Commerce, being ſome crafty <hi>Italian</hi> or <hi>Portugues,</hi> who (du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of the late, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Cardinal</hi>) have amaſſed very
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169778:62"/>conſiderable Eſtates, and great Riches And here we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly obſerve, That no <hi>Gentleman</hi> will in <hi>France</hi> binde his yongeſt ſon to any <hi>Trade</hi> or <hi>Mechanique Calling</hi> whatever, under that of a <hi>Military life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Appren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor in France.</note> as eſteeming eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Apprentiſage</hi> and ſubjection, a ſtain and diminution to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and Dignity of his <hi>Family;</hi> the like alſo, they for the moſt part obſerve in their <hi>Marriages</hi> and <hi>Alliances:</hi> but herein the <hi>German</hi> is moſt religious.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Nobility and Gentry</hi> of this Kingdom differ much from the <hi>garb</hi> of living in <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilities Garbe of living in France.</note> both within, (and till of late) without doors: They have many of them vaſt eſtates, either in Lands or Offices; the Revenues whereof they chuſe rather to ſpend at <hi>Paris,</hi> and other great Cities, in a ſpecious <hi>Retinue</hi> of <hi>Coaches, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> and <hi>Laquaies,</hi> then ſuffer themſelves to be eaten up at <hi>home</hi> in the country in the likeneſſe of <hi>Beef and Muſtard,</hi> among their
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169778:63"/>unthankful <hi>Neighbours.</hi> This af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of theirs to reſide for the moſt part in the chief <hi>Towns</hi> of the Kingdom,
<note place="margin">Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> is the reaſon why the <hi>Corporations</hi> are little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, as not daring to be brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hatching ſuch <hi>Factions,</hi> as where the Gentry and civiller ſort of Mankinde are univerſally given to <hi>ſolitary</hi> and <hi>unactive lives</hi> in the country. Beſides, the Gentlemen are generally gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to thoſe laudable Magnificen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of <hi>Building,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the Nobility &amp; Gentry.</note> and furniſhing their <hi>Palaces</hi> with the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Moveables, much of the <hi>luxe</hi> and <hi>exceſſe</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> being now far entred amongſt them, as may well ſerve to exemplifie, when in the <hi>Dutcheſs of Chaulmes</hi> her Palace neer the <hi>Place Royal in Paris,</hi> the <hi>pennaches,</hi> or tuſts of plumes belonging to one of her <hi>beds</hi> onely, is eſtimated worth <hi>fourteen thouſand livers,</hi> which amounts to neer a <hi>thouſand pounds</hi> ſterling of our money.</p>
            <p>Every <hi>great Perſon</hi> who builds
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169778:63"/>here,
<note place="margin">Great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to learning.</note> however qualified with <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuals,</hi> pretends to his <hi>Elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory</hi> and <hi>Library:</hi> for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of which laſt, he doth not much amuſe himſelf in the particular elections of either <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> or <hi>Impreſſions;</hi> but having erected his caſes and meaſured them, accords with a <hi>Stationer</hi> to furniſh him with ſo many <hi>gilded Folioes,</hi> ſo many <hi>yard of quarto's,</hi> and <hi>octavo's</hi> by the great, till his <hi>Bibliotheke</hi> be full of Volumes. And yet ſome of them, both have excellent books, and are very po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite <hi>Scholers:</hi> but the <hi>Nobleſſe</hi> do not naturally ſo addict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſtudie, as the <hi>Gown-men</hi> do; accounting it a life ſo <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templative,</hi> and below their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<note place="margin">Phyſick and Law deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Nobility of France.</note> that no <hi>Gentlemans</hi> neceſſity whatſoever ſhall eaſily engage him to ſeek any ſupport, either by <hi>Phyſick</hi> or <hi>Law:</hi> both which <hi>Profeſſions</hi> are (as in truth they highly merit) in very laudable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and reputation amongſt us in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:169778:64"/>
            <p>The <hi>State Eccleſiaſtick</hi> (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending that of the <hi>Religion</hi>) is of two ſorts;
<note place="margin">State Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick of France.</note> the greater part whereof being <hi>Pontificians,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proteſtants.</note> commonly called thoſe of the <hi>Religion,</hi> (and by them with this adjunct, <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endue Reformée</hi>) who exerciſe the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> of France are nothing ſo preciſe,
<note place="margin">Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cks of Fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, how they differ from others of the ſame Religion.</note> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and <hi>bigotiſh</hi> as are either the <hi>Recuſants</hi> of <hi>England, Spain,</hi> or <hi>Italy;</hi> but are for the moſt part an <hi>indifferent ſort of Chriſtians,</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally not ſo ſuperſtitious and devout, nor in ſuch <hi>Vaſſallage</hi> to his <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> as in other parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> where the ſame opinions are profeſſed; which <hi>indifferency,</hi> whether I may approve of, or condemn, I need not declare here.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>poor Proteſtants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proteſtants, how eclipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of late.</note> they are now ſo inconſiderable, ſince the late Succeſſes of the <hi>Cardinal Richlieu,</hi> and eſpecially our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169778:64"/>reproach,</hi> and their misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune at <hi>La Rochelle;</hi> that for the preſent they poſſeſs no one place of ſtrength, or any other ſingular immunity above others, as being defeated of all <hi>Eminent Perſons,</hi> either of <hi>Birth</hi> or <hi>Charge,</hi> who might be able to defend or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel them at need; the <hi>Court</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now rendred moſt of them <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> by <hi>Preferments</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts,</hi> or other effectual means: Howbeit, ſuch as remain (and of which too there are likewiſe a very conſiderable body) are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted peaceably to enjoy their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> upon renovation of the late <hi>Edict of Pacification;</hi> and are undoubtedly, in caſe of any conſiderable <hi>Rebellion,</hi> capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to form a very ballancing and pondrous party; but with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that <hi>front</hi> and confidence which within theſe <hi>twenty years</hi> paſt, they might have done; when they durſt even beard the <hi>King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The cauſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and protect ſuch as retired to them, from his diſpleaſure, in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169778:65"/>moſt of his, now ſtrongeſt Towns and places of <hi>Importance:</hi> But the <hi>Scean</hi> is now much altered, and they ſhrewdly contracted, eſpecially ſince the ſtir under that late and incomparable perſon, the <hi>D. of Rohan:</hi> the folly of their own private Intereſts, having e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently proved their fatal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; as it is moſt frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeen to fall out (firſt or laſt) amongſt all contrivers of <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Popular Diſſentions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fate of civil diſſentions. Little Schiſm a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Proteſtants, betwixt themſelves, and why.</note> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, thus far I muſt needs vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the <hi>Proteſtants of France,</hi> That we finde not amongſt them thoſe frequent <hi>Schiſmatiques</hi> and broachers of ridiculous <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſms,</hi> as abound amongſt us; every particular ſo unanimouſly concurring with their <hi>Paſtor,</hi> That, in truth, they are herein not unworthy to be commended; though that <hi>vertue</hi> likewiſe were the more eſtimable, were it not certainly conſtrained by the vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy of their <hi>Antagoniſts,</hi> who watch all advantages to diſcom,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169778:65"/>poſe, and defame them. To be ſhort, though they have loſt many great ones, and much ſtrength, and that the form of their Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline invite few, yet the light of their attempts hath invited ſo many to look into the reaſon of things beyond the mask of <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> and <hi>myſtery</hi> of <hi>Policy,</hi> that it is both thought, and well known, That even divers of thoſe who are perſons of greateſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency, both in <hi>Church and State,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inclinations of many great ones to a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> have ſo good an inclination to change ſome points of the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved opinions, That were it not more out of <hi>ſecular</hi> conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to loſe their preferments, then any other inconveniency, many of them would openly <hi>profeſs</hi> themſelves <hi>Janſenianiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Janſenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liniſts.</note> 
               <hi>Mouliniſts, &amp;c.</hi> Whoſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as they infinitely propagate amongſt them, ſo do they come on a great way towards a <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Forces of France</hi> is that which renders it (as indeed it doth
<note place="margin">Forces of France.</note>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:169778:66"/>all other Kingdoms) moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable <hi>abroad,</hi> and ſecure at <hi>home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Frame</hi> and <hi>Poſiture</hi> of the <hi>Continent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſite of France.</note> ſituated as it were in the <hi>Navel</hi> of all the <hi>Chriſtian World,</hi> qualifies it to collect, unite and diſpoſe of her forces; for it hath <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> before it, <hi>England</hi> behinde; The <hi>Seas</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the right, and <hi>Germany</hi> upon the left-hand; at one corner the <hi>Neatherlands,</hi> and the <hi>Cantons</hi> of the <hi>Suiſſe</hi> at the other; all of them potent, conſiderable, and active <hi>Neighbors;</hi> and where they intermit, it is a worthy proſpect to behold, how <hi>Nature</hi> hath ſerved and defended her with the <hi>Pyrenes, Alps, Ocean,</hi> and <hi>Mediterranean Seas,</hi> whileſt ſhe ſitting ſecure from any ſubitane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous irruption or natural <hi>pretenſion,</hi> may well be pronounced, a fair and moſt <hi>Juſt Empire;</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſince the later acceſſion of <hi>Bretagne, Guyenne, Normandy</hi> (once the goodly portions of the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169778:66"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi>) and <hi>Bourgogne,</hi> who are now all of them under one <hi>Prince,</hi> as having enjoyed hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every one their proper <hi>Dukes;</hi> by whoſe favor or ſpleen there was always a facile entrance for any potent ſtranger to diſturbe the reſt of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequencies whereof, have filled almoſt every modern <hi>Chronicle.</hi> And to the ſtronger twiſting of this Cord, ſuch prudence hath been had of late times, that all thoſe great and powerful houſes remain now no more divided (as ſtill amongſt the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi>) the <hi>Cadets</hi> and yonger <hi>Brothers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cadets and yonger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all Soldiers of Fortune.</note> minding for the moſt part no greater preferments, then what they cut out with their Sword, and merit in <hi>Field</hi> by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Soldiers</hi> of <hi>Fortune.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Forces by Sea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Francis the firſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, and why?</note> as it was never great, ſo we do not read, That ever any ſignal <hi>action</hi> hath been atchieved by any of their <hi>Navigations;</hi> for which cauſe, <hi>Francis the firſt,</hi> was once
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169778:67"/>pritty well reſolved to make uſe of the <hi>Turk,</hi> and call in that ſtout <hi>Miſercant,</hi> to the eternal reproach, both of that <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Nation;</hi> notwithſtanding, at this inſtant,
<note place="margin">Maritime Forces and Havens.</note> their <hi>Maritime</hi> ſtrength is not totally ſo contemptible, having a very ſtately and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Armada</hi> of handſom <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> in moſt of their <hi>Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean Ports,</hi> as at <hi>Toulon, Marſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>illes,</hi> and other places, which are Veſſels of excellent uſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice upon thoſe <hi>Seas:</hi> On the <hi>Ocean,</hi> I confeſs, both their <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping</hi> and <hi>Traffique</hi> have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like trivial; and yet of late, they have greatly augmented their Fleet, eſpecially ſince the time (to our <hi>Nations</hi> egregious ſhame and diſhonor) that they have made ſo large inroads and gaps into <hi>Flanders,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Late Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſts.</note> towards the <hi>Sea Coaſts;</hi> Witneſs thoſe ſtrong Towns and Havens of <hi>Dunkirk, Mardike, &amp;c.</hi> Stout Forts, and very commodious Harbors for <hi>ſhipping;</hi> ſo that a little time (if
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169778:67"/>we will ſtill ſuffer it) may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe furniſh them with Ships enough to make them ſtand in a bolder competition with their Neighbors.</p>
            <p>But the more principall Nerve of the French <hi>Power</hi> conſiſts in his <hi>Forces at Land;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Land Forces</note> and amongſt them (as hath already been touched) chiefly his <hi>Cavalry,</hi> which is of ſtrength and ſpectacle both of admiration and gallantry,
<note place="margin">Cavalry of France the beſt of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</note> they being for the greater part compoſed of <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> who ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſo bequeath themſelves to this ſervice, that hee who (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them) hath not <hi>made</hi> two or three <hi>Campagnas</hi> (as they uſe to term it) by that time he is 18 yeers of age (is eſteemed as a perſon <hi>laſche,</hi> that is, of a ſoft education and ſmall repute: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<note place="margin">The Horſe an exerciſe proper to the French youth. Their Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demies and other Gym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſticks.</note> the <hi>Horſe</hi> is an exerciſe unto which they have ſo naturall a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and addreſſe, that the whole earth doth not contain ſo many <hi>Academies</hi> dedicated chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to this Diſcipline, &amp; other mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169778:68"/>
               <hi>Gymnastiques,</hi> wherein they handſomly attain to competent perfection in whatſoever is active and proper for their youth and inclinations.</p>
            <p>And what incomparable <hi>ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers</hi> this Country hath in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges bred,
<note place="margin">Souldiery of France com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</note> we need look out no further for teſtimony, then their many paſt and preſent Acquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Enterpriſes, under <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court, Condy, Gaſſion,</hi> and infinite others: beſides, (what is no tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial mark of our aſſertion) the multitudes of ſuch who are at preſent imployed in the Services of Forraign Princes. Very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyable it is,
<note place="margin">Spaniſh and Fr. Inſantry compared</note> that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Infantry is too hard for the <hi>French</hi> Foot: for the <hi>Peaſants</hi> of <hi>France</hi> (of whom they ſhould na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally conſiſt) are thought (and that upon good grounds) to be more then accidentally improper and <hi>mal-adroict</hi> for that ſervice: Howbeit, we finde (and that by quotidian experience) that <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> or ſomething elſe more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169778:68"/>hath much altered and reformed their Natures, even in this particular inſtance: And for ought I perceive, they keep what they have gotten, and become as good Soldiers, as thoſe who brag ſo much of their <hi>lowſie</hi> and <hi>tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Epitheton:</hi> But I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, how few <hi>Indigene</hi> and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſerve now againſt them; all the old brave foot having been for the greater part ſlain, or continued unrecruted, at and ſince the ſignal Battel of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croy,</hi> where (thogh with their own deſtinies) they bravely made good that general and worthy repute w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the world hath of the <hi>Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> of that Nation. And however, had this reproach a more ſolid ground,
<note place="margin">A ſaying of Machiavel.</note> yet that ſaying of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavel</hi> in his <hi>Ritratto,</hi> That <hi>Le Fanterie che ſi fanno in</hi> Francia <hi>non poſſono eſſer buono per che gli è, gran tempo che non hanno hauuto guerra, e per queſto non hanno ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienza alcuna, &amp;c.</hi> Is now no more an Argument, Then that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169778:69"/>the <hi>premiſes</hi> being changed, the Concluſion muſt needs remain, conſidering that the <hi>Cauſe</hi> being taken away, through their preſent exerciſe, and perpetual <hi>War,</hi> the <hi>Effect and Defect</hi> cannot of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence enſue, as we have already ſufficiently proved: or admit it were yet ſo, I hope the <hi>Suiſſe</hi> and other faithful <hi>Mercenaries</hi> to that Crown, abundantly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all theſe wants and prejudices; moſt of which, yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for my part, were, I think, firſt hired rather out of conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>diverſion,</hi> and ſince <hi>cuſtom,</hi> then otherwiſe out of any pure neceſſity. That likewiſe which made the <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>France</hi> ſo inconſiderable for native Foot Soldiers, may with much reaſon too (if we pleaſe) be attributed unto <hi>Lewis the Eleventh</hi> his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arming of the <hi>Commons;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conſequence of diſarming the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> by which advice, the <hi>King</hi> indeed became more <hi>abſolute</hi> at home amongſt his <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> but a great deal leſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable <hi>abroad</hi> amongſt his <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies:</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:169778:69"/>And herein it was, that his <hi>Neighbors</hi> ſtood him in ſtead.</p>
            <p>Another thing rendring this <hi>Kingdom</hi> very conſiderable for an <hi>Army,</hi> is,
<note place="margin">France a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant in people and Victuals.</note> their <hi>Prolifique</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying; for <hi>Europe</hi> embraceth not a more <hi>populous Nation,</hi> nor more abounding in <hi>Victuals,</hi> which is the <hi>belly</hi> of that cruel Beaſt, called <hi>War;</hi> ſo <hi>Fertil,</hi> I ſay it is, That when <hi>Charls the fift</hi> entred into <hi>France</hi> by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence,</hi> and afterwards by <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paigne,</hi> it nouriſhed (beſides the many Garriſons thereof) more then an Hundred and fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Ravenous Soldiers; and even in the time of <hi>Charls the ſixth,</hi> there were found in this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> Twenty thouſand Horſe, and Thirty thouſand Foot, all conſiſting of ſtrangers; and Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thouſand Horſe, and One hundred thouſand Foot, all of <hi>Natural French.</hi> And verily, when we have ſeriouſly ſurveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the complication of <hi>Enemies,</hi> which once inveſted this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:169778:70"/>when for <hi>Extent</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> it was far inferior to what it is at preſent, ſince the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have been diſpoſſeſſed, <hi>Navar</hi> adjoyned, and other additions of great ſtrength: I ſay, when <hi>England, Germany, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> invaded it on all parts, in the Reign of <hi>Francis the firſt,</hi> as it will appear, how potent and able this Kingdom united, is to defend it ſelf: So doth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of it ſeem to me moſt ſtrange, and altogether porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous.</p>
            <p>Adde to theſe advantages,
<note place="margin">Store of Arms, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, and Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> their ſtore of good <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> excellent <hi>Artillery,</hi> many famous and well furniſhed <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines;</hi> in ſum, Why ſhould I farther tire you with particulars, when their preſent <hi>Exploits,</hi> and almoſt continual <hi>Triumphs,</hi> have planted the <hi>Flower de Lyces</hi> where ever they break ground. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thoſe renowned adventures ſince <hi>Charlemaigne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ancient and late Acquiſts</note> 
               <hi>St. Lewis, Charls d'Anjou, Charls the eighth,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169778:70"/>&amp;c.</hi> whoſe Heroicque Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and glorious Trophies, have filled all Hiſtories and Countreys, even as far as <hi>Aſia</hi> her ſelf; witneſs their Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Succeſſes at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Barbary, Cyprus, Greece, Naples, Saxony, Hungary,</hi> and ſundry other places, even in theſe our times, and before our own doors; witneſs all their late <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſts</hi> and <hi>Conqueſts</hi> in <hi>Catalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Spain, Italy, Flanders, &amp;c.</hi> Beſides the Signal Battels and Sieges of <hi>Nordlingen, Rocroy, Perpignian, Theonvil, Arras, Dunkirk, &amp;c.</hi> Not to repeat the miraculous, or rather ingenious reduction of <hi>La Rochel, Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelier,</hi> and other impregnable holds appertaining to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants:</hi> So that if now we ſee them begin to decline, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fund what they have ſo haſtily ſwallowed down, it is but the common fate of all <hi>humane under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fate of all humane Enterpriſes</note> all things having a period in this World, that had a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:169778:71"/>
            <p>And now,
<note place="margin">Church neer a third part of France.</note> albeit the <hi>Church</hi> (who is neer a good third part of <hi>France</hi>) doth in moſt places (as the Proverb goes) neither loſe nor defend any thing; yet here in times of publick and emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſſities, have they been made contribute moſt bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards the maintaining of <hi>Armies</hi> and Supplyes.</p>
            <p>Nor are the <hi>Frontiers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Frontiers &amp; Maritime coaſts how fortified at preſent.</note> and <hi>Maritime</hi> coaſts of this Kingdom ſo ill fortified now, as in former times; but there hath been of late ſo through a reformation and care had in that regard, that it were hard to call to minde a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable place at preſent but is capable to ſupport a long and ſtrenuous reſiſtance; eſpecially thoſe Harbours and Keys of the Countrey which reſpect our Coaſts: as <hi>Haver, Calais, Diepe,</hi> and divers other places of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance.</p>
            <p>In fine,
<note place="margin">State of Fr. at preſent.</note> 
               <hi>France</hi> is at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent grown to that <hi>ſtature,</hi> ſo well <hi>planted,</hi> and commodiouſly
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169778:71"/>laid to it ſelf, that (but for their own madneſſe, and the feared fate of theſe times, which already begins to work) in the reall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt &amp; balance with her <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">High time that a Non ultra were fixed to her greatneſſe.</note> it were high time ſhe were now a little obſerved, and a <hi>Non ultra</hi> fixed unto her proceedings and future aſpirings: Nor doubt I at all, but if the <hi>Low Countries</hi> were able to preſerve her <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality,</hi> but <hi>England</hi> with <hi>Spain</hi> (as poor and contemptible as ſhe is now grown) may one day ſo exerciſe this ambitious Kingdom, as ſhe may be glad to contain her ſelf within her own Confines, without moleſting or incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of her <hi>Neighbours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I deny not,
<note place="margin">The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spain ſuſpicious, and how far it concerns us.</note> that even the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Spain</hi> her ſelf were as much to be apprehended, equally as dangerous, did not her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed ſwelling and unnatural <hi>Plethory</hi> moſt certainly incline to a <hi>Tympanie,</hi> rather then ſhew it proceeded from any ſtrong and <hi>ſane conſtitution:</hi> their over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſping
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169778:72"/>humour,
<note place="margin">The humour of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard liken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> being much like his, who deſiring a good handfull of <hi>ſand,</hi> by griping it over hard, loſeth more through his fingers, then he can carry away in all his palm:
<note place="margin">England's beſt bulwark and balance.</note> So that in this caſe, our onely beſt Bulwark is <hi>France;</hi> and <hi>(vice verſâ)</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ'd to their power, <hi>Spain,</hi> ſo long as this <hi>antipathie</hi> amongſt them continues, and they remain in one entire bodie. For this cauſe it was,
<note place="margin">Qu. Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths policy</note> and for no other, that <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> would very wiſely by no means conſent to that offer of <hi>Cantonizing</hi> this Kingdom, when in the time of the late <hi>League</hi> ſhe was offered a conſiderable ſhare. But on the other ſide,
<note place="margin">Danger in the Acceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries to Fr.</note> the Acceſſion of the <hi>Low Countries</hi> to this Empire, were beyond all compariſon more perillous, then if they had alſo never ſtarted aſide from their lawfull <hi>Maſter;</hi> and this by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their <hi>Situation, Vicinity, Ports, Traffick, Towns of defence,</hi> the infinite diſadvantages where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169778:72"/>we ſhould ſoon acknowledge to our coſt and ignominy.</p>
            <p>As touching the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> they are yet ſo numerous in <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">That the Spaniard hath no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienate the French ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, by his inſtruments the Jeſuits, and why?</note> and the <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> ſo averſe in that point, as there can never ſpring up the leaſt appearance of hope that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould ever pretend any thing in this Country by way of inclination or defection; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the late <hi>Jeſuites</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all thoſe ſtrict <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Bans</hi> made againſt them) begin to ſwarme and re-eſtabliſh themſelves. And ſo I have done with the more generall remarks worthy your conſideration. I ſhal onely ſay a word or two of the <hi>people,</hi> and of <hi>Paris</hi> in particular, and ſo finiſh this task.
<note place="margin">Genius and nature of the people.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> that which the <hi>Prince of Politicians</hi> gives out of the <hi>French,</hi> where he affirms, that <hi>I Franceſi ſono per natura piùfieri, che gagliardi ò de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri,</hi> Upon what <hi>Ceſar</hi> of old
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169778:73"/>ſaid of the <hi>Galli Inſubres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caeſars ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Galli Inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres.</note> that in the beginning they appeared more then <hi>Men,</hi> but proved in the concluſion leſſe then <hi>Women,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in it ſtill ſomething of their preſent promptneſſe, and as ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den diſcouragement: Upon which obſervation, the fore-cited <hi>Florentine</hi> notably adviſeth, <hi>Chi vuole ſuperare j Franceſi ſi guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di dal primo loro impeto, &amp;c.</hi> That he who would vanquiſh the <hi>French,</hi> ſhould be ſure to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and break their firſt <hi>brusk</hi> and onſet; becauſe they uſually ruſh on upon danger like a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and in a deſperate fury, when they firſt charge and joyn battell:
<note place="margin">French fury at onſet.</note> but as nothing which is violent is permanent, ſo <hi>expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> as ſoon ruines, and utterly daunts their courage.</p>
            <p>But as for their <hi>Intellectuals,</hi> and more noble part, ſuch of them as dedicate themſelves to Letters and <hi>Erudition,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Learned men in France.</note> prove as polite <hi>Scholers</hi> and as trim Wits as any <hi>Italian</hi> of them all. The
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169778:73"/>greater part of them, I confeſſe, and ordinary <hi>Pretenders,</hi> pleaſe themſelves more in <hi>Analyticall</hi> and curſory ſpeculations, to which one may take <hi>poſt</hi> at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>pillar</hi> in the ſtreets,
<note place="margin">Pedantry of ſome profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</note> where you ſhal never fail of ſome braga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docio <hi>Hippias,</hi> who like ſome <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectus univerſalis,</hi> profeſſes, and will undertake to render any man an exact and perfect <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, Divine, Orator, Chymiſt;</hi> or to teach him all <hi>Languages,</hi> and indeed, what not, within the ſpace of a month or two: which kind of Table Method and <hi>Lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian art,</hi> renders many of them, even to the very <hi>Mechanicks,</hi> moſt egregious talkers, and intolerably <hi>pragmaticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Add unto this,
<note place="margin">Their level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> their <hi>levelling of Learning,</hi> and <hi>laying all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors in common,</hi> by their intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate <hi>Tranſlations,</hi> having but of very late put all the <hi>Orations of Cicero</hi> into <hi>French,</hi> as it is long ſince that the <hi>Poets</hi> have been made <hi>Orators:</hi> for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169778:74"/>more frequent then the turning of them into <hi>proſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt the <hi>Faculties of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Paris</note> there are ſome good and <hi>dextrous Divines;</hi> but their School <hi>Exerciſes</hi> are dull and perfunctory things, in competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with what was wont to be performed here in our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Generally,
<note place="margin">Phyſicians &amp; Chirurgians of Prance, their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and ill ſucceſſe.</note> the <hi>Chirurgians</hi> of <hi>France</hi> are Pretenders to <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and the <hi>Phyſician</hi> as great a friend to the <hi>Emperick;</hi> eſpecially in point of <hi>Phlebotomie,</hi> which is their <hi>Panacea</hi> for all Diſeaſes. And albeit they have bred ſome able and accompliſh'd <hi>Proficients</hi> of all theſe kindes; yet their common practice in tedious and <hi>Chronique,</hi> as well as acute diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, imports them rather to a ſudden eaſe of the <hi>patient,</hi> then any intire recovery, or ſecurity from relapſe; for they ſtudy more to weaken and enervate the Body, then the Diſeaſe: ſo that they recover few of <hi>languiſhing Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:169778:74"/>which <hi>relapſe</hi> not as ſoon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and for the moſt part pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: contrary both to the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> and ſucceſs of our <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in <hi>England;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Praiſe of Engliſh Phyſicians.</note> into one of whoſe hands I had rather put my <hi>life,</hi> then to a whole <hi>Colledg</hi> of theſe <hi>French Leaches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Mechanicks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">French Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable.</note> they are univerſally <hi>excellent, inventive,</hi> and <hi>happy;</hi> and are of late too become far more ſtay'd and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> in point of <hi>habit</hi> and <hi>faſhion</hi> then they were wont to be: for I will undertake, our native levity and wantonneſſe in that kinde, hath of late yeers infinitely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French Children</hi> are the faireſt letter that <hi>Nature,</hi> I think,
<note place="margin">French chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and youth.</note> can ſhew through all the humane <hi>Alphabet;</hi> but though they be <hi>Angels</hi> in the <hi>cradle,</hi> yet are they more like <hi>Divels</hi> in the <hi>ſaddle:</hi> age generally ſhewing, that what ſhe ſo ſoon beſtowes, ſhe takes as faſt away; for the <hi>French</hi> (after twenty) preſently ſtrike forty in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169778:75"/>their faces, and eſpecially amongſt their <hi>Women,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sudden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> who are then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely decayed, when ours, if not <hi>beautifull,</hi> are yet very <hi>tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> at thoſe years; which, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it proceeds from the <hi>ſiccity</hi> of the air, <hi>drinking water, ill diet,</hi> or other <hi>accident,</hi> I dare not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily determine; and yet I am the rather inclined to think, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that nature it muſt needs be, when we finde the <hi>women</hi> of <hi>Quality</hi> for the moſt part as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Beauties as any the whole world produces, without diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging <hi>our Ladies</hi> at home, whom I would be unwilling this <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph</hi> ſhould in the leaſt degree offend.</p>
            <p>I cannot affirm that the <hi>youth</hi> of the <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>Nobleſſe</hi> of <hi>France</hi> are bred altogether ſo <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate</hi> as moſt of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> are;
<note place="margin">Youth of the French Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try not bred to letters, and why?</note> being, as I ſaid, of leſſe <hi>phlegme,</hi> and more prompt then to fix to thoſe unactive ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; Nor are they at all ſo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and inquiſitive in their <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels,</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:169778:75"/>unto which fewer alſo are inclined,
<note place="margin">Humour in Travelling.</note> but ſeem abundantly ſatisfied, to be able to ſay, They have been in ſuch, or ſuch a place.
<note place="margin">No truſt to the cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>earance</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is a true obſervation of one, That a <hi>French man</hi> appears a <hi>child</hi> at all ages; but in practice and negotiation you ſhall finde him a <hi>man.</hi> It is the <hi>Field</hi> and <hi>Court</hi> which the <hi>Gentry</hi> affect as the beſt of Education;
<note place="margin">Indifferency of the Fr. in religion.</note> and thence I am inclined to beleeve, they contract amongſt them that <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency</hi> of beleeving and living, in which they are generally more open and free then even the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The French not ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banched as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Engliſh youth at preſent.</note> albeit yet not in all points ſo <hi>enormous</hi> as the depraved youth of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe prodigious <hi>diſbaucheries</hi> and late unheard of extravagancies, far ſurpaſſe the madneſſe of all other <hi>civilized Nations</hi> whatſoever.
<note place="margin">Nor more given to Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</note> 
               <hi>Gaming</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they frequent,
<note place="margin">Nothing ſo much to drink and tobacco.</note> but are in no one vice ſo abandoned, as to the exhauſting their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in point of <hi>drink</hi> and <hi>Tobacco;</hi>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:169778:76"/>which, though it have of late got ſome footing upon the more <hi>vile ſort,</hi> and infected ſome <hi>Northern parts</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> yet few perſons of Quality uſe either in <hi>exceſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">but adorers of bread and pottage.</note> But what they do not in <hi>drink,</hi> they pay in <hi>bread,</hi> and are ſtrange devourers of <hi>Corn;</hi> they adore a <hi>good pottage</hi> (whatever the reſt of the <hi>Repaſt</hi> be) as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did <hi>garlick:</hi> nor will a true <hi>Monſieur</hi> be brought at any rate to taſte a glaſſe of wine, <hi>ſans premier manger;</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they neither do ſo much, nor ſit ſo long at it, yet they uſe to <hi>collation</hi> more often, the moſt temperate of them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>paſſions</hi> of the people are ſuddenly imported and puffed up with a <hi>Victory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Elevated &amp; dejected ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly with victory or loſſe.</note> and as ſoon deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the leaſt repulſe or loſs. They are prodigall,
<note place="margin">Splendid in externals.</note> and ſplendid in <hi>externals,</hi> but ſeldome undoe themſelves in <hi>houſe-keeping and hoſpitality:</hi> The beſt ſort eat like <hi>Princes,</hi> and far exceed our Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; the <hi>common</hi> worſe then
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169778:76"/>
               <hi>dogs:</hi> generally, ſo they flouriſh and appear for a <hi>month or two</hi> in the <hi>Summer,</hi> they will fare hard enough the reſt of the yeer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides;
<note place="margin">Full of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</note> and ſuch as minde onely their profit, have little <hi>charity,</hi> where they ſee no evident <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi> They are exceedingly <hi>cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> and have generally their <hi>tongues well hung;</hi> which promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of theirs,
<note place="margin">of a joviall converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, handſom addreſs, and well ſpoken</note> as it becomes them well in <hi>encounter,</hi> ſo they are for the moſt part, of <hi>joviall converſation,</hi> and far from that conſtrained addreſſe which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall to our <hi>ſullen Nation,</hi> who never think our ſelves acquainted, till we treat one another with <hi>Jack and Tom;</hi> familiarities,
<note place="margin">Cenſure of the rude fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie of the Engliſh.</note> which, as we finde no where elſe in uſe, ſo they commonly termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in vaine and rude Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> are the ſole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Europe</hi> that do <hi>idolize</hi> their <hi>Soveraign,</hi>
               <note place="margin">French re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verencers of their King.</note> unto whom the have likewiſe a more free and immediate <hi>acceſſe</hi> (without much
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:169778:77"/>
               <hi>ceremony</hi>) then ordinarily is to be ſeen in any other <hi>Princes Court:</hi>
               <note place="margin">and his affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to them.</note> and this affabilitie and freedom gains them as ſtrangely to him; which (certainly) is an excellent art in the one, and no leſſe a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in the other. But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, their <hi>choler</hi> throughly ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, there never wants ſome <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliac</hi> or <hi>cut-throat</hi> to perpetrate their malice; ſo unſtable is <hi>popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar confidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally,
<note place="margin">Their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and hate of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh.</note> they have a naturall dread and hate to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as eſteeming us for the moſt part, a fierce, rude, and barbarous <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> but their <hi>antipathy</hi> to a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi> is deadly and irreconcilable.</p>
            <p>For their <hi>Bodies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stature,</note> they are both Sexes of <hi>mean ſtature,</hi> rather in <hi>good point,</hi> then either lean or groſſe;
<note place="margin">complexion,</note> generally, ſwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, except ſuch as have mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Eaſt:</hi> the <hi>Women</hi> have commonly <hi>black eyes, rare teeth,</hi> and <hi>ſweet voyces;</hi> and certainly, ſo gentile and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall an <hi>addreſſe</hi> even in their
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169778:77"/>moſt ordinary actions, that one may as eaſily diſtinguiſh them by <hi>it,</hi> as their <hi>tongues:</hi> In fine,
<note place="margin">promptneſs,</note> they are extremely <hi>prompt,</hi> and imagine to comprehend all upon an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> which makes many to give out and tire in the journey before they be half way: for all which,
<note place="margin">and cheerful ſupinity of the people.</note> and their oppreſſions to boot, there lives not under the <hi>cope</hi> of <hi>heaven</hi> a more <hi>frank galiard,</hi> and <hi>ſupine</hi> people: howbeit many of them will not ſtick to <hi>repine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Victories unwelcom, to the Fr. and why?</note> and cenſure even their own <hi>Victories</hi> and ſucceſſes, whereof every one but ſeems to add a heavier weight to their <hi>Oppreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now,
<note place="margin">The beſt &amp; moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Map of a Country.</note> as every <hi>Metropolitan</hi> and <hi>Royal</hi> City is likely the beſt <hi>Map</hi> of the <hi>Country</hi> wherein it ſtands; ſo may <hi>Paris</hi> be eſteem'd the moſt exact <hi>Compendium</hi> of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paris is a City</hi> in a <hi>Ring,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paris, ſite, Edifices, &amp;c.</note> whereof the <hi>Louvre</hi> or Palace of the King is the <hi>Diamond:</hi> And truly, conſidering the vaſtneſſe of its circumference, ſo incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169778:78"/>built all of the <hi>living Rock,</hi> whereupon it is ſeated (which for beauty, eaſie working, and laſtingneſs, renders it a prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence above many more coſtly Materials) I think no <hi>City</hi> in the whole world equalizes it. I have ſeen <hi>Naples, Rome, Florence, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa,</hi> and <hi>Venice;</hi> all ſtately Cities, and full of Princely <hi>Fabricks;</hi> but then I compare the extent, and here are many <hi>Centuries</hi> of <hi>Noblemens Houſes,</hi> both within the Town and the Environs, which altogether approach, if not exceed the beſt of them. This I will boldly affirm, that for the <hi>Streets, Sububrs,</hi> and <hi>common buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,</hi> it infinitely excels any City elſe in <hi>Europe:</hi> for publick <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,</hi> ſome of the <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> are fair Foundations and handſome Piles; but the <hi>Convents</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> come far ſhort of the Towns before recited: yet that of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> are not much inferiour to ſome of the beſt and moſt modern Pieces
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169778:78"/>of <hi>Architecture</hi> extant.</p>
            <p>The <hi>River of Seine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The River of Seine.</note> which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides it, is nothing comparable, for ſweetneſſe and good conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to our <hi>Royal</hi> River of <hi>Thames:</hi> yet it would deceive any man in the <hi>uſe,</hi> when he ſhall ſeriouſly examine and conſider the huge <hi>Veſſels</hi> of burden (though not <hi>Ships</hi>) it brings up, full of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities</hi> and neceſſary <hi>Proviſions.</hi> In concluſion, <hi>Paris</hi> wants nothing but <hi>clean Streets,</hi> and a redreſſe of the multitude of <hi>Coaches, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quays,</hi> and throngs of <hi>Mankind;</hi> with all which,
<note place="margin">Number of people &amp;c. in Paris too great.</note> it is generally ſo <hi>peſtered,</hi> that it appears a miracle to me, how ſo many <hi>backs</hi> are <hi>clothed,</hi> and <hi>bellies</hi> maintained (in a Town of no eminent Staple) as you may behold in one day, if you walk the ſtreets and publick <hi>Carfours;</hi> Moſt of the <hi>Houſes</hi> ordinarily harbouring <hi>ſix,</hi>
               <note place="margin">True cauſe of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineſſe.</note> as often <hi>ten families</hi> betwixt <hi>heaven</hi> and <hi>hell,</hi> the <hi>Garrets</hi> and the <hi>Cellars:</hi> and this I take to be the true cauſe of that <hi>Nastineſſe</hi> which we uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169778:79"/>impute to the <hi>Nation: Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Perſons of quality more neat and ſumptuous then any in England.</note> and ſuch as have room enough, being far more <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>ſumptuous</hi> in their houſes, then the beſt of us here in <hi>England,</hi> however we arrogate the <hi>contrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the <hi>Extent of this City,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The extent of Paris and London dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to be compared, and why?</note> it hath been, and is ſtill a great controverſie amongſt our Countrey-men <hi>Travellers,</hi> which is the larger, <hi>This</hi> or <hi>London,</hi> every one ſpeaks according to his inclinations: But the <hi>figures</hi> of them both are ſo different, that it would be a very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult matter to reconcile them, by making an exact tryall: and peradventure, all things conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; there is as yet no very great inequality: but if we may conjecture from the buildings at preſent,
<note place="margin">Prodigious increaſe of buildings.</note> and prodigious enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their <hi>Suburbs</hi> on all ſides, what a little time and <hi>Peace</hi> will render it, it muſt, without doubt, in a ſhort time outgrow the contention, and far exceed it.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169778:79"/>for I finde no end of their ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting not onely of particular <hi>houſes,</hi> but even of whole <hi>ſtreets,</hi> and thoſe ſo incomparably fair and <hi>uniform,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beauty of the now new Edifices of Paris.</note> that you would i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine your ſelf rather in ſome <hi>Italian Opera,</hi> where the diverſity of <hi>Scenes</hi> ſurpriſe the beholder, then beleeve your ſelf to be in a reall <hi>Citie.</hi> This is onely to be obſerved in their prime <hi>Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings</hi> and <hi>Palaces,</hi> that the beſt <hi>Fabricks</hi> commonly promiſe leſs towards the <hi>Front</hi> or Street, then you will finde them within the <hi>Court;</hi> which is cauſed by the high walls and <hi>tarraces</hi> that thwart them: a piece of <hi>Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,</hi> which in other <hi>Appearances</hi> and outſides they do not uſually practiſe.</p>
            <p>But what our <hi>City of London</hi> hath not in houſes and <hi>Palaces,</hi>
               <note place="margin">London for Shops, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Schools, and Noiſe, exceeding all C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ies of the world.</note> ſhe hath in <hi>Shops</hi> and <hi>Taverns;</hi> which render it ſo open by day, and cheerfull in the night, that it appears to be a perpetuall <hi>Wake,</hi> or <hi>Wedding</hi> to the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169778:80"/>for ſo <hi>mad</hi> and lowd a <hi>Town,</hi> is no where to be found in the whole world.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Policy</hi> of this <hi>Preveſté</hi> is exerciſed by <hi>Judges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Paris.</note> called <hi>Lieutenants Civils</hi> and <hi>Criminels;</hi> who, for pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing their <hi>Offices</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> ſell their Juſtice at extraordinary rate, to ſuch as have uſe of that rare <hi>Commodity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prevoſt of Merchand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> They have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a <hi>Prevost of the Merchands, &amp; les Eſchevins,</hi> which is an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice more reſembling our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder</hi> and <hi>Sheriff,</hi> then <hi>Major:</hi> Likewiſe the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> hath a ſpirituall juriſdiction here;
<note place="margin">Archbiſhop of Paris, &amp;c.</note> as alſo ſome particular <hi>Abbots</hi> and <hi>Priors:</hi> And with all this, I cannot ſay, it is well governed; the diſorders of every day and night will convince me,
<note place="margin">Diſorders of Paris in the night, how they might be prevented</note> if I ſhould, when ſo many execrable <hi>Murthers</hi> and <hi>Villanies</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the ſtreets; an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience which might yet be eaſily prevented, if they would but imitate our <hi>Policy,</hi> and form
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169778:80"/>their <hi>Watches</hi> of conſtant and reſponſible perſons.</p>
            <p>Neither is the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of this renowned City any thing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in ſtreſſe of a <hi>Siege,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Strength of Paris no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in a ſiege.</note> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of other naturall advantage, ſave onely fire: nay, ſo open it is to the <hi>Conquerour,</hi> that <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nys</hi> (which lies but two leagues remote from it) hath oftentimes been the <hi>Frontier of France;</hi> &amp; had not the late <hi>Mareſchal de Gaſſion</hi> as deerly,
<note place="margin">Mareſchal de Gaſtion preſerved Paris from the Spany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard.</note> as bravely purchaſed their <hi>Liberty</hi> at the ſignal battel of <hi>Rocroy,</hi> the <hi>Spainyard,</hi> 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, might (without the leaſt obſtacle, have marched up to the very gates of <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the incomparable <hi>Aire</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> is that which fortifies the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Aire of Paris cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated.</note> ſo that very ſeldom hath a <hi>Plague</hi> or other <hi>Epidemical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion</hi> made here that havock and lamentable <hi>devaſtation,</hi> which it ſo frequently doth in our putrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>climate,</hi> and accidentally ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>focated <hi>City:</hi> contrary to that <hi>Vulgar</hi> (but moſt falſe) <hi>Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:169778:81"/>which I find in every mans mouth;
<note place="margin">The ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tradition amongſt us, that the plague is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver out of Paris, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> that the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> is never out of <hi>Paris:</hi> but this (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>ſiccity</hi> of the aire) many <hi>Naturaliſts</hi> aſcribe to the over <hi>ſulphurous</hi> exhalations of the ſtreets, and dry attracting quality of the <hi>Plaſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quality of the Plaſter of Paris.</note> which, bears or gives the <hi>Name</hi> to this <hi>goodly ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Cert è id firmiſſimum Imperium eſt, quo obedientes gaudent.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>Thus, Sir, by the <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance</hi> of your <hi>Patience,</hi> I have adventured to draw the <hi>Curtain,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering a very ample <hi>Theatre,</hi> in a ſhort time, and repreſented it in as
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169778:81"/>narrow a <hi>Circumference,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Artiſts</hi> who intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a multitude of <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> through an <hi>Optick,</hi> into ſome dark room or cloſet: And the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude peradventure will not appear <hi>unapt,</hi> when you conſider the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Method,</hi> and <hi>confuſed Stile</hi> in which it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. But as wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Hiſtories</hi> is not my <hi>Trade,</hi> I know you have not commanded me to undergo this <hi>Task,</hi> to make thereby any advantage of my <hi>Imperfections,</hi> but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:169778:82"/>mine <hi>Obedience.</hi> And now, although I doubt not but many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Perſons</hi> have moſt excellently treated upon this very <hi>Subject,</hi> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to their <hi>Times;</hi> yet I will be bold to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, and that <hi>ſans va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> none hath lately performed it with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>faith, ſuccinctneſſe,</hi> and in more <hi>natural Colours.</hi> For hee that will truely comprehend the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Genius</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> muſt <hi>proſpect</hi> and look out every day for new <hi>diſcoveries; France</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:169778:82"/>being now no more the thing it was <hi>forty yeers</hi> ſince, then the <hi>garb</hi> and <hi>faſhion</hi> at that time, to the <hi>habit</hi> and <hi>Mode</hi> now in uſe amongſt them, equally as <hi>different,</hi> as <hi>incomparable:</hi> And in truth, (to diſabuſe the World) the <hi>complexion</hi> and <hi>Craſis</hi> of this Body <hi>Politick</hi> is of ſo high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to the <hi>health,</hi> and good eſtate of our poor <hi>Nation,</hi> that to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevre her in entire <hi>habit</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> there can never be too often <hi>inſpections</hi> into the <hi>State</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:169778:83"/>and <hi>Regiment</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom.</hi> This is the opinion of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Paris, <date>this 15 of Febr. 1652. Stilo novo.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir, </salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Friend, and moſt obedient Servant, <hi>J.E.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:169778:83"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
